<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The preachers precept of consideration, or, Englands chief lesson and duty in this sad time of visitation wherein is contained, 1. A catalogue and collection  of all the particular capital sins mentioned in Scriptures ... 2. The author's opinion and judgment, for which and why it is, that this unparallel'd visitation is now laid upon us / delivered in the parish church of St. Katherine Coleman, London, upon the monthly fast-days set apart for humiliation, by His Majesties special command.</title>
            <author>Dobson, Jeremiah.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1665</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 118 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A36233</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1799</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32815</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12770113</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12770113</idno>
            <idno type="VID">93632</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A36233)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93632)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1033:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The preachers precept of consideration, or, Englands chief lesson and duty in this sad time of visitation wherein is contained, 1. A catalogue and collection  of all the particular capital sins mentioned in Scriptures ... 2. The author's opinion and judgment, for which and why it is, that this unparallel'd visitation is now laid upon us / delivered in the parish church of St. Katherine Coleman, London, upon the monthly fast-days set apart for humiliation, by His Majesties special command.</title>
                  <author>Dobson, Jeremiah.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 42 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E. Cates for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLXV [1665]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Dobson by Wing and NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages stained with loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Plague --  England --  History --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:93632:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93632:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>THE Preachers Precept OF CONSIDERATION:</hi> OR, Englands <hi>chief Leſſon and Duty In this ſad time of VISITATION.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherein is contained,</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>1.</hi> A Catalogue and Collection of all the particular capital Sins mentioned in Scripture, whereby ſometimes <hi>Princes,</hi> and ſometimes <hi>People,</hi> have provoked God to inflict this <hi>ſore Judgment</hi> upon a Nation.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>2.</hi> The Authors opinion and judgment, for which and why it is, that this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parallel'd Viſitation is now laid upon us.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Delivered in the Pariſh Church of St.</hi> Katherine Coleman, London, <hi>upon the Monthly Faſt-dayes ſet apart for</hi> Humiliation, <hi>by His Majeſties ſpecial Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON: <hi>Printed by</hi> E. Cotes <hi>for the Author,</hi> M. DC. LXV.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:93632:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:93632:2"/>
            <head>THE PREACHERS PRECEPT OF Conſideration.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ECCLES. VII. 14.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>In the day of Proſperity be Joyfull, but in the day of Adverſity Conſider.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T's the Wiſemans obſervation before, <hi>Chap.</hi> 3.1. <hi>That to every thing there is a ſeaſon, and a time to every purpoſe under the Sun:</hi> particularly, <hi>verſ.</hi> 4. <hi>there is</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>a time to weep, and a time to laugh; a time to mourn, and a time to dance.</hi> And reaſon good that it ſhould be ſo; for ſeeing that mans preſent condition is ſubject to many and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent alterations: our Life, like the Sea, ebbing and flowing, and with the Air, being now cloudy, and anon clear; ſeeing that <hi>Nulla ſors longa eſt,</hi> as the<note n="(a)" place="margin">Seneca: Thyeſt.</note> 
               <hi>Tragedian</hi> ſayes very truly,<note n="(b)" place="margin">Job 14.2.</note> 
               <hi>We continue not long in one ſtate;</hi> but<note n="(c)" place="margin">Cartwright in Eccles.</note> 
               <hi>Sicut noctis &amp; diei, hyemis &amp; aeſtatis viciſſitudo eſt; i. e.</hi> As the day hath the viciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitude
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:93632:3"/>of an evening and morning, and the year of a Winter and Summer; ſo Health and Sickneſs, Peace and War, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity and Adverſity interchangeably ſucceed each other, in this our earthly pilgrimage: what therefore is more rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal, fit, and natural, than that as our outward condition is various and mutable, ſo likewiſe our inward diſpoſition of minde ſhould be anſwerable, and our ſpiritual frame, be ſutable to our temporal Eſtate? This I am ſure hath been the practice of the true children and ſervants of God in all ages, who in dayes of Affliction and publick Calamity, alwayes ſought unto God with <hi>Prayers and Tears, with Faſting and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation;</hi> and after Deliverance and Reſtauration, uſed to ſet forth the glory of his Name with <hi>Anthems of joy and exultation:</hi> they wiſely and with due conſideration, imployed and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed their hearts and tongues to utter before <hi>God,</hi> either <hi>Hoſanna's</hi> or <hi>Hallelujahs,</hi> ſometimes <hi>Prayers,</hi> and ſometimes <hi>Prayſes,</hi> as occaſion required. And as this was the <hi>Saints Practice</hi> every where and in all ages; ſo 'tis the <hi>Wiſemans Precept</hi> here, <hi>In the day of proſperity be joyful, but,</hi> &amp;c. Which latter clauſe I ſhall confine my Diſcourſe unto, as conteining in few words, both very much, and very good ſeaſonable ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice for this ſad time of <hi>Viſitation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the whole ſentence, though it may ſeem that there is not a direct oppoſition in words and terms, yet we ſhall find the expreſſion more emphatical and didactical, than if it had been ſo. The <hi>Wiſeman</hi> indeed does not ſay, <hi>In the time of proſperity be joyful, and in the day of adverſity be ſorrowful,</hi> but <hi>conſider:</hi> And the reaſon as I conceive is this, Becauſe <hi>outward ſorrow</hi> may be worldly and carnal, ſelfiſh and hypocritical, yeilding neither honour nor glory to <hi>Gods holy Name,</hi> nor yet any ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage or comfort to the party affected therewith: for men many times are of <hi>a ſad countenance, and</hi> (as our bleſſed Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ſpeaks, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.16.) <hi>do disfigure their faces on purpoſe that they may appear unto men to be ſorry,</hi> and there is all. But an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and ſerious, a deep and religious conſideration never fails to bring forth the fruits and good effects that God ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects. This is that which makes a man enter into his Cloſet, that ſo he may <hi>commune with his own heart,</hi> hear his caſe tryed
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:93632:3"/>in the <hi>Court of Conſcience,</hi> humble himſelf in duſt and aſhes, and poure forth his ſoul in ſecret to <hi>God; Who</hi> never fails (as our Saviour there ſhews, <hi>verſ.</hi> 4, 6, 18.) not only <hi>to own and regard,</hi> but alſo <hi>to crown and reward</hi> all ſuch <hi>ſecret acts of devotion, openly.</hi> Whereas the <hi>Wiſeman</hi> therefore here doth not ſay, <hi>Be ſad and ſorrowful in the time of adverſity,</hi> but <hi>conſider;</hi> I conceive it is becauſe the expreſſion is much more emphatical, comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive, and didactical (as I ſaid before) and doth indeed directly point out, and plainly teach us, without any kind of circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locution, what is the main duty that God expects and requires at our hands in times of Affliction and Tribulation, and that is <hi>to Conſider.</hi> And truly no wonder, for of <hi>This</hi> it may well be ſaid, That <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>i. e.</hi> virtually it is <hi>every good Duty:</hi> For as much as we know that <hi>Self-examination, Self-accuſation, and Condemnation, Prayer and Supplication, Repentance, Faith in Gods Promiſes, Reſolutions of new Obedience,</hi> &amp;c. they are all the fruits that ſpring from this root; <hi>they</hi> are all conceived (as 'twere) in this <hi>Wombe; they</hi> are the ſpiritual <hi>brood</hi> and <hi>offspring;</hi> but <hi>Conſideration</hi> is the <hi>Alma Mater,</hi> the heavenly <hi>Parent</hi> and <hi>Mother</hi> of them. <hi>Conſideration!</hi> 'tis <hi>Spiritus Sancti quaedam Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brica vel Officina, i. e.</hi> the ſpiritual ſhop and workhouſe (as it were) of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> wherein he ſecretly forgeth and faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oneth upon the Anvil of a truly <hi>broken and contrite heart,</hi> all the pieces of that excellent <hi>armour of proof,</hi> that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which the Apoſtle ſpeaks of <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6. In a word, <hi>Conſideration!</hi> 'tis the <hi>Handmaid</hi> of ſpiritual Knowledge, and the <hi>Miſtreſs</hi> of all true Devotion; without which no acceptable ſervice can be performed by us to <hi>God.</hi> Whereas, if men would but now and then beſtow an hour or two in ſerious thoughts, and ſoberly <hi>conſider</hi> how the caſe ſtands betwixt <hi>Almighty God</hi> and their ſouls; whether they be in a <hi>ſtate of Grace,</hi> or <hi>of Nature;</hi> of <hi>Peace with God,</hi> or <hi>under Wrath;</hi> and, <hi>What they muſt do that they may be ſaved:</hi> doubtleſs, they would find themſelves bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter diſpoſed to the <hi>ſervice of God,</hi> than now they are: For the truth is, the principal reaſon that ſo many perſons in the world are no better, is, becauſe they will not <hi>Conſider,</hi> and ſeriouſly meditate on their ſpiritual ſtate and condition. The cares and affairs, the profits and pleaſures of this life, do ſo wholy
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:93632:4"/>ingroſs their <hi>hearts</hi> and imploy their <hi>heads,</hi> that the concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of their immortal precious ſouls, and the things of another life, are not regarded. And hence it is that the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours of faithful Miniſters are ſo unſucceſsfull; the good and ſerious advice of Friends and Parents is no more followed; and all the <hi>Means of Grace,</hi> and methods of God for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming of ſinful Offenders, affect no more, and operate no better; namely, becauſe they will not <hi>conſider. Hear O Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, and give ear O Earth,</hi> (ſayes <hi>Almighty God</hi> himſelf by the Prophet, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.2, 3.) <hi>The Ox knoweth his owner, and the Aſs his Maſters crib: but Iſrael doth not know, my people doth not not Conſider.</hi> Yea, hence it is, that though <hi>life and death, good and evil,</hi> (as<note n="(d)" place="margin">Deut. 30.15.</note> 
               <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpeaks) <hi>are ſet before us,</hi> and <hi>put to our choice;</hi> yet the generality of people in the world, live as perſons not at all concerned whether there be a God or no; an Heaven, or an Hell; eternal Joyes, or everlaſting Torments. So that a ſerious <hi>conſideration</hi> is very good and neceſſary for us even at all times: but the moſt proper ſeaſon for it (as <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us) is the <hi>time of affliction; In the time of Adverſity Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whence the point of Doctrin that offers it ſelf to our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration is this:</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>That when Gods Judgements are in the Earth, and the ſad tokens of his diſpleaſure appear againſt a Perſon, or a Nation, then it's a proper ſeaſon for them ſeriouſly to lay things to heart, and wiſely to conſider.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The guiſe and cuſtom of all Atheiſtical Epicures, and graceleſs Worldlings, is quite contrary; who when any croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, diſaſters, or loſſes are in <hi>judgement</hi> inflicted upon them, do not retire into their Cloſets, and there enter into a ſerious me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation of the matter, <hi>communing with their own hearts,</hi> and <hi>conſidering</hi> who it is that ſmites them, and for what: but either with Curſing, Oaths, and Execrations, they break forth into repining and murmuring againſt Gods diſpenſations towards them, which many times end in Deſpair; or elſe they run to the Tavern or Alehouſe, that ſo in the jovial company of good fellows, they may drown the ſenſe of all ſorrow and care, and <hi>thwart</hi> and <hi>non-plus</hi> (if it be poſſible) the end and deſign of God
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:93632:4"/>in puniſhing them. His good end certainly was to humble them, and reclaim them from their iniquities, but they liſten not to the <hi>voyce of his Rod,</hi> but <hi>in laetitiam &amp; luxum proſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liunt,</hi> reſolve to take their full ſwinge in voluptuouſneſs; ſaying,<note n="(e)" place="margin">Wiſd. 1.6, 7, 8, 9.</note> 
               <hi>Let us eat and drink, and enjoy the good things of this life; let us Crown our ſelves with Roſe-buds, and leave tokens of our mirth and jollity in every place.</hi> This is the common deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and practice of the ungodly in <hi>time of adverſity.</hi> And this they are either betrayed into by their own <hi>deceitful, vile, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal hearts;</hi> or elſe they are byaſſed by the great and general cuſtom of the world; or elſe they are prompted to it by <hi>Satan;</hi> who knows full well that a <hi>due and ſerious Conſideration</hi> would take them from him, and make them quickly renounce and abhor all wicked wayes: And therefore it is, that he doth ſtill with all his might and ſubtilty ſtrive to divert and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade them from it, as a moſt childiſh, ſad, and dumpiſh me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy courſe, which probably may endanger their health, but can otherwiſe do them no good. Whereby it appears, that the more neceſſary any Duty is, the more oppoſite Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan and our falſe carnal hearts are thereunto: For there is not a more advantagious, uſefull, and profitable, nor a more excellent, heavenly and acceptable Duty (as I ſhall ſhew more fully hereafter) for a good Chriſtian to be exerciſed in at all times, and upon all occaſions, in all eſtates and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, eſpecially in <hi>the day of adverſity,</hi> than this of a <hi>ſerious Conſideration.</hi> And therefore it is that <hi>Almighty God</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends it unto us ſo much in Scripture, as a ſingular means to help and direct us how to ſteer our courſes aright: as <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.29. <hi>Oh that they were wiſe; that they underſtood this, that they would conſider their latter end.</hi> Pſal. 4.4. <hi>Stand in awe, and ſin not, commune with your own hearts, and be ſtill.</hi> Prov. 4.26. <hi>Ponder the path of thy feet, and let all thy ways be eſtabliſhed;</hi> and Hag. 1.5, 7. <hi>Now therefore, thus ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider your wayes.</hi> In which remarkable place, the Adverb <hi>Now,</hi> and Conjunction <hi>Therefore,</hi> plainly point out the <hi>Time</hi> and <hi>Occaſion, when</hi> and <hi>wherefore</hi> God required them to practiſe this duty of <hi>Conſideration. The Children of Iſrael</hi> being brought home to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> again, out of their long Captivity
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:93632:5"/>in <hi>Babylon,</hi> were exceeding backward and negligent in their carrying on the work and building of <hi>the Houſe of the Lord.</hi> Forward enough it ſeems they were to erect and prepare ſumptuous buildings, and neat habitations for themſelves; the Prophet calls them <hi>cieled Houſes,</hi> (v. 4.) but <hi>the houſe of the Lord, they let that lye waſte, pretending</hi> (forſooth, <hi>v.</hi> 2.) <hi>that it was not a fit time yet to doe it.</hi> This was their Crime. Now the <hi>Judgment</hi> which God inflicted upon them for it, was that of <hi>Famine,</hi> as <hi>v.</hi> 6, 9, 10, 11. <hi>Ye looked for much, and lo, it came to little; and when ye brought it home, I did blow upon it: and why, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts? becauſe of mine Houſe that is waſte, and ye run every man to his own houſe. Therefore the Heaven over you is ſtayed from dew, and the Earth is ſtayed from her fruit: And I called for a drought upon the Land, and upon the Mountains, and upon the Corn, and upon the new Wine, and upon the Oyl, and upon that which the ground bringeth forth; and upon Men, and upon Cattel, and upon all the labour of the hands.</hi> Surely a deplorable, ſad, and moſt miſerable ſtate and condition. And what is now the duty that <hi>God, the great Phyſician of Souls,</hi> puts them upon here by the Prophet; and that both in order to a ſpeedy and thorow Reformation of themſelves, as well as for the happy procuring of his loving kindneſs, and gracious reconciliation towards them? Why, it is nothing but this, <hi>Conſider your wayes.</hi> A duty, which the Prophet <hi>Haggai</hi> ſeems to look back upon as an <hi>Inſtar omnium:</hi> and therefore it is obſervable, that he preſſeth no other duty upon them in the whole Prophecy. Neither doth he content himſelf to deliver his Meſſage <hi>au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritativè,</hi> with a [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> &amp;c.] <hi>thus ſaith the Lord of Hoſts,</hi> as here in this Chapter; but again afterwards to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force the ſame, he earneſtly prayes and intreats them to fall upon the ſpeedy performance of it; as <hi>Chap.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 15. to 20. Which frequent inculcation of the Precept, ſerves to teach us two things by the way:</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The ſtrange ſtupidity of the People; in that they were no more affected with thoſe manifeſt marks and tokens of Gods indignation; no, though he had ſnatched their very Meat out of their mouths. And then,</item>
               <item>2. The great neceſſity of the Duty in times of diſtreſs. So
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:93632:5"/>that when <hi>Gods Judgments are in the Earth, and the ſad tokens of his diſpleaſure appear againſt a Perſon or Nation, then its a proper ſeaſon for them ſeriouſly to lay things to heart, and wiſely to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>In the proſecution of this Point, I do intend to proceed in this method:<note place="margin">Method.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. By way of Explication, to acquaint you with the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Duty</hi> in general; as alſo the <hi>Subject matter</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; touching withall a little upon the two great <hi>Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> of moſt convenient <hi>Time</hi> and <hi>Place.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. By way of Confirmation, to ſubjoyn ſome Reaſons for the proof of the Point.</p>
            <p n="3">3. To bring all home to our ſelves in an effectual Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For the firſt of theſe, <hi>Conſideration</hi> in general, <hi>It is a deliberate ſerious Act of the practical part of mans <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Explication.</note> 
               <hi>whereby he reflects and muſeth upon both his own Actions, and Gods Diſpenſations; and by comparing the one with the other in the Court of Conſcience, and according to the Rule of Gods holy Will revealed in his Word, he draws up Concluſions againſt himſelf, and ſecretly takes up good Reſolutions to juſtifie God, and to repent and reform himſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. As for the <hi>Subject matter</hi> of it, it may be conſidered either more <hi>generally,</hi> or more <hi>ſpecially.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>More <hi>generally,</hi> the ſubject matter of our <hi>Conſideration</hi> ſhould be the viſible <hi>cauſes</hi> and <hi>conſequences</hi> of things; the evident Outgoings of God in the world, and the preſent Operations of his hands, and that both more privately as to our ſelves, as well as more publickly as to the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State</hi> where we live; all things indeed that happen either to our ſelves or others that we are any way related unto, whether caſually and accidentally, ſo far as we can ſee, or by an apparent <hi>hand of Providence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>More <hi>ſpecially,</hi> in <hi>the day of adverſity,</hi> the time here ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in my <hi>Text,</hi> the Subject matter of our Conſideration ſhould be theſe five things following:</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The Affliction it ſelf, the Evil, Diſaſter, or Viſitation, whatever it be that is befalne us.</item>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:93632:6"/>
               <item>2. The Author and the Diſpenſer of it.</item>
               <item>3. The Ground, or the procuring and Meritorious Cauſe of it.</item>
               <item>4. The End, or the minde and meaning of God therein.</item>
               <item>5. The good way and means that we are to uſe, that ſo it may be removed from us, or at leaſt we may have it ſanctified to us. I content my ſelf with the bare naming of theſe things here in the <hi>Explication,</hi> becauſe I intend to inlarge my ſelf to the full upon them in the <hi>Application.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="3">3. Now the two <hi>Circumſtances</hi> of moſt convenient <hi>Time</hi> and <hi>Pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce</hi> follow. And</p>
            <p n="1">1. For <hi>Place;</hi> though it be indifferent in reſpect of God, whether it be <hi>in the field with Iſaac,</hi> or in the <hi>houſe with Daniel,</hi> at home or abroad, walking or ſitting; yet I conceive that a ſolitary, and a <hi>Place</hi> ſet apart for pious purpoſes is the moſt proper and fit for this Exerciſe: And ſuch in particular are our own <hi>private Walks</hi> and <hi>Cloſets;</hi> to which our <hi>Saviour</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf directs us, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.6. Or elſe the publick <hi>Houſe of Gods Worſhip;</hi> which<note n="(f)" place="margin">Heb. 10.24, 25.</note> St. <hi>Paul</hi> would have us frequent for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, according to the example of King <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 27.4. And then,</p>
            <p n="2">2. For <hi>Time;</hi> the <hi>Lords Day</hi> in particular is the moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per time in the Week, and ordinarily calls upon us, as well as thoſe <hi>Solemn Days of Faſting and Humiliation</hi> do in extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary manner put us in minde of this duty. But though it muſt be chiefly intended on thoſe <hi>Holy-dayes,</hi> yet it muſt not be neglected on other days, but ſome time convenient muſt be ſet apart for this good work every day. As for the hour, or preciſe ſpace of time in the day, each mans own <hi>Experience</hi> muſt inſtruct him, and his <hi>Occaſions</hi> direct him; whether to take the golden hour of the Morning, when he is moſt freſh, free from diſtraction, and fitteſt for Meditation; And thus<note n="(g)" place="margin">Gen. 28.16.</note> 
               <hi>Jacob</hi> did: Or the ſtill hour of the Evening, when he hath ended his labours; which was<note n="(h)" place="margin">Gen. 24.63.</note> 
               <hi>Iſaacs</hi> time: Or the middeſt of the day; which was<note n="(i)" place="margin">Acts 10.9.</note> St. <hi>Peters:</hi> Or elſe any other part of the day, if not all three; which, as it appears, were holy <hi>Davids,</hi> and devout <hi>Daniels</hi>
               <note n="(k)" place="margin">Pſal. 55.19. &amp; Dan. 6.10.</note> 
               <hi>hours of devotion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I mention here theſe two <hi>Circumſtances</hi> of <hi>Time</hi> and <hi>Place,</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:93632:6"/>becauſe I know them to be very uſefull and neceſſary helps and furtherances for all ſuch as deſire to perform this duty to purpoſe; I mean, ſo as to reap <hi>benefit</hi> and <hi>comfort</hi> by it. For, to ſay nothing of the natural averſneſs and indiſpoſition of our own <hi>hearts</hi> to this good work, nor yet of <hi>Satans</hi> ſubtil ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions, and ſecret oppoſition whereby he ſtrives to keep us back, or at leaſt interrupt and take us off from it; ſuch and ſo great are moſt mens hinderances and diſtractions, ſo many are the Obſtructions and Obſtacles that they meet with (part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly through multiplicity of buſineſs, their worldly employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments at home and abroad; partly through the mutability of their mindes and diſpoſitions, with the inſtability of their affections and roving Fancies) that unleſs ſome convenient <hi>Times</hi> and <hi>Places</hi> be ſet a part for the exerciſe of it, it is very likely to be performed but ſleightly and ſuperficially, uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly, and unprofitably, nay perhaps not at all by them. <hi>There is</hi> (as the<note n="(l)" place="margin">Eccl. 3.1.</note> 
               <hi>Wiſe man</hi> tells us) <hi>an appointed Time for every thing</hi> elſe; and ſhall then ſo weighty, ſo concerning a <hi>Duty</hi> as this have no ſhare in it; which yet might juſtly challenge our attendance upon it at all times? And as for ſome cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and ſet place, 'tis likewiſe as neceſſary; becauſe we ſhall finde the leaſt and feweſt <hi>Impediments</hi> there, where we are moſt accuſtomed to draw neer to God either in Reading, Prayer, or Meditation. Our<note n="(m)" place="margin">John 18.1, 2. with Luk. 22.39, 40.</note> 
               <hi>Saviour</hi> himſelf (I am ſure) took this courſe, and alſo uſed his <hi>Diſciples</hi> to it, and then well may we follow <hi>his</hi> and their example, as an excellent means to make us both more carefull, and conſtant in the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of holy duties.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I ſay, <hi>carefull,</hi> as to the <hi>manner; (ſanctè magìs quàm ſcitè,</hi> as he<note n="†" place="margin">Seneca.</note> ſays well) in regard we have now placed our ſelves in the <hi>preſence of God,</hi> and are come to converſe and make our addreſſes immediately to <hi>Him,</hi> who is <hi>The ſearcher of the heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Conſtant,</hi> as to the <hi>Matter;</hi> the revolution of time being a certain <hi>Remembrancer</hi> of the duty: the wilful, the negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, or excuſatory omiſſion whereof, when the prefixed time is come, is that which occaſions the great unfitneſs and indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſition that many complain of.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:93632:7"/>
            <p>And ſo I have done with the <hi>Explication:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Confirmation.</note> the <hi>Confirmation</hi> now follows; and the Reaſons of the Point are three.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> 1. Becauſe, <hi>To lay things ſeriouſly to heart, and religiouſly to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider in the day of Adverſity</hi> is the moſt proper Anſwer and Eccho to <hi>Gods</hi> correcting angry hand, and that ſpiritual im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement which <hi>He</hi> expects that we ſhould make of <hi>His</hi> chaſtiſing us. <hi>The Lords voyce cryeth unto the City,</hi> (ſays the<note n="(n)" place="margin">Micah 6.9.</note> Prophet) <hi>and the man of Wiſdom ſhall ſee thy Name: hear ye the rod, and who hath appointed it.</hi> Whence we may gather, that as <hi>God</hi> ſpeaks to men by his <hi>Word,</hi> even ſo <hi>He</hi> ſeems to call out, and cry to them by the <hi>Voyce of his Rod:</hi> And the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal end in the firſt place is, to make them liſten, <hi>ſtand ſtill,</hi> and <hi>conſider</hi> what is his minde and meaning thereby. It is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable in that excellent Prayer of King <hi>Solomons</hi> at the Dedication of the Temple, that one Petition very pertinently to our purpoſe runs thus,<note n="(o)" place="margin">1 King. 8.37, 38, 39.</note> 
               <hi>If there be in the Land a Famine, if there be Peſtilence,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>whatſoever Plague, whatſoever Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs there be; What Prayer and Supplication ſoever be made by any man, or by all thy people</hi> Iſrael, <hi>which ſhall know every man the Plague of his own heart, and ſpread forth his hands towards this Houſe: then hear thou in heaven thy dwelling place, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give,</hi> &amp;c. Whence it appears, that the duty of ſeeking to Him by Prayer, which cannot be done without <hi>Conſideration,</hi> is that which God in the firſt place expects and looks for <hi>in the evil day,</hi> before men muſt think to obtain deliverance. The want whereof he ſorely complains of, as you heard<note n="(p)" place="margin">Iſa. 1.2, 3.</note> before: So <hi>Amos</hi> 4.6, 8, 10, 11. where notwithſtanding his hand was againſt the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in divers reſpects, <hi>Yet have ye not returned unto me, ſaith the Lord;</hi> and <hi>Jer.</hi> 8.6. <hi>I hearkened, and heard, but they ſpake not aright: no man repented him of his wickedneſs, ſaying, What have I done?</hi> Again,</p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> 2. Becauſe, <hi>a religious, due, and ſerious conſideration</hi> is the moſt expedite and compendious way, I, and indeed the only me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod preſcribed in Scripture for the obtaining of Gods favour and Reconciliation. <hi>David</hi> firſt <hi>conſidered his wayes</hi>
               <note n="(q)" place="margin">Pſal. 119.59.</note> 
               <hi>before he turned his feet to Gods Teſtimonies:</hi> And the Prodigal Son <hi>came firſt home</hi>
               <note n="(r)" place="margin">Luk. 15.17.</note> 
               <hi>to himſelf,</hi> by the <hi>conſideration</hi> of his lewd courſes, before he came home back again to his Father. So
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:93632:7"/>that Converſion, true Repentance, and Reformation, always begin at <hi>Conſideration,</hi> but it ſtill happily ends with the <hi>love and favour of God.</hi> For, when once a ſinful Perſon or Nation by a Religious ſelf-reflexion have learned to renounce all their iniquities and evil deeds, then<note n="(s)" place="margin">Pſal. 103.13.</note> 
               <hi>Like as a Father pitieth his Children, even ſo the Lord,</hi> with that compaſſionate Father of the Prodigal, is ready to <hi>run to embrace and receive them,</hi> with the ſweeteſt evidences and demonſtrations of his love and favour:<note n="(t)" place="margin">Iſ 4.55.7. &amp; Ezek. 18.21. Joel 2.12, 13, 14. &amp; Zech. 1.3.</note> 
               <hi>Let the wicked forſake his ways, and the unrighteous man his thoughts, and let him return unto the Lord, and he will have mercy upon him, and to our God, for He will abundantly pardon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>3</label> 3. Becauſe this impartial and faithful dealing betwixt God and our own ſouls, in a religious, due, and ſerious <hi>Conſideration,</hi> is an infallible token and evidence of our ſincerity; and ſo muſt needs prove an excellent Cordial to chear us up in <hi>the day of adverſity.</hi> Hypocriſie may teach men to multiply out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide performances, and make them ready to ſay to others, as ſometime <hi>Jehn</hi> did to <hi>Jehonadab,</hi>
               <note n="(u)" place="margin">2 King, 10.16.</note> 
               <hi>Come with me, and ſee my zeal for the Lord;</hi> for all that <hi>ſuch</hi> doe (as our Saviour ſhews) is <hi>that they may be ſeen of men.</hi> But ſincerity draws the heart inward, and never let's a man be at reſt untill he have made his peace with God. For which end, it puts him upon ſelf-examination, ſelf-accuſation, hearty repentance, prayer and ſupplication, with reſolutions of new obedience, and a ſerious <hi>conſideration</hi> in general how for the future he may do moſt good, and may beſt lay forth himſelf for the <hi>honour and glory of God.</hi> Now when this great work is done, there is nothing can happen amiſs to that man; the inward <hi>teſtimony of his own Conſcience</hi> is to Him a <hi>Continual Feaſt,</hi> and now he finds by hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py experience, <hi>that all things cannot chooſe but work together for his good: Chriſt</hi> is his <hi>Friend,</hi> by Faith in whoſe merits his peace and reconciliation is wrought with <hi>Almighty God,</hi> and then what cares he who is his <hi>Foe? Heaven</hi> is his <hi>home,</hi> and then what cares he what he may ſuffer by the way? <hi>that</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">2 Cor. 4.17.</note> 
               <hi>far more exceeding and eternal weight of glory,</hi> he knows will outweigh, and abundantly compenſate all thoſe <hi>light and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentany afflictions</hi> that may befall him here upon Earth; nay,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:93632:8"/>he is ſure there is no<note n="(x)" place="margin">Rom. 8.18.</note> compariſon betwixt them. And therefore he reſolves to <hi>fight a good fight, and keep the faith,</hi> yea though it be with the loſs of his life, as being aſſured <hi>that</hi>
               <note n="(y)" place="margin">2 Tim. 4.7, 8. Rom. 8.35, 37.</note> 
               <hi>henceforth there is layd up for him a Crown of righteouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are the reaſons of the point; by all which it appears, that if we deſire either, 1. To anſwer Gods expectation, and make a wiſe and profitable improvement of <hi>His</hi> chaſtiſing hand upon us; Or, 2. To enjoy the ſweet tokens and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences of <hi>His unſpeakable love and favour,</hi>
               <note n="(z)" place="margin">Pſal. 63.3.</note> 
               <hi>which is better than life;</hi> Or elſe, 3. Have any comfortable argument of our ſincerity, and ſo ſome good ground of joy and comfort in the worſt of calamities, then we muſt <hi>ſeriouſly lay things to heart, and religiouſly conſider in the day of Adverſity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> And if it be ſo, <note place="margin">Of Reprehenſion. Branch <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> this then juſtly ſerves to reprove and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn thoſe that live in carnal ſecurity, and inconſiderately, I, and perhaps incorrigibly too, ſtill run on in their vain evil wayes, as if they were not at all concerned. They know very well, or at leaſt have frequently heard from <hi>Gods Word</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 6.23.</note> 
               <hi>that the wages of ſin is death:</hi> and they have been taught, how<note n="b" place="margin">Heb. 10.31.</note> dreadful and <hi>fearful a thing it is to fall into the hands of the living God,</hi> who <hi>is indeed</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Heb. 12, 29.</note> 
               <hi>a conſuming fire.</hi> But yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, as if they <hi>had made a</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Iſa. 28.15.</note> 
               <hi>Covenant with death, and with hell were at an agreement,</hi> and the loſs of Gods loving kindneſs and favour were not conſiderable, they are apt <hi>to put from them the evil day,</hi> and think they have ſtill time enough to repent, preſuming, that although <hi>the overflowing ſcourge paſs through the City, or the whole Land, yet it ſhall not come nigh unto them;</hi> and ſo they run on in their <hi>evil courſes, after</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Rom. 2.5.</note> 
               <hi>their hardneſs and impenitent heart, treaſuring up wrath unto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves againſt the moſt dreadfull day of wrath.</hi> Now againſt this ſort of men the<note n="f" place="margin">Iſa. 5.11, 12.</note> 
               <hi>Prophet</hi> juſtly denounceth <hi>a Woe;</hi> for <hi>the harp, the viol, the tabret and pipe, and Wine are in their Feaſts; but they regard not the work of the Lord, neither conſider the operations of His hands. In that day</hi> (ſayes<note n="g" place="margin">Iſa. 22.11, 12, 13.</note> he very ſmartly) <hi>the Lord God of hoſts called to weeping, and to mourning, and to baldneſs, and to girding with ſackcloth: But behold joy and gladneſs, ſlaying oxen, and killing ſheep; eating fleſh and drinking wine; Let us eat and drink, for to morrow we die.</hi> And what then follows? <hi>It
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:93632:8"/>was revealed in mine ears by the Lord of hoſts; Surely this ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity ſhall not be purged from you till you dye, ſaith the Lord God of hoſts.</hi> It is a moſt wretched frame of ſpirit for men to grow ſecure in ſin, and <hi>not learn righteouſneſs, when as Gods judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are in the earth,</hi> and his hand of Vengeance is ſtretched forth, not with a <hi>ſcourge of Cords</hi> but <hi>Scorpions,</hi> to puniſh and plague them for their iniquities. This is a ſign of deſperate wickedneſs, and the principal cauſe I verily believe, why the judgments of God in this preſent fore <hi>Viſitation</hi> are<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Septemb.</hi> 6. 1665.</note> ſtill ſo long, and ſeverely executed upon us, and his wrath ſeems dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtill to wax hotter and hotter againſt us: The <hi>Lord God</hi> of heaven be graciouſly pleaſed to touch our hard hearts, and make us ſadly reflect upon it: Remember, I pray you, that terrible Viſion of the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> concerning <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> which both in reſpect of the cauſe and effects of Gods indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, ſeems too too applicable at this time to this populous <hi>City of London.</hi> The <hi>cauſe</hi> of Gods anger you will find was that, which we muſt now needs confeſs our ſelves to be guilty of, <hi>viz. The iniquity of the houſe of</hi> Iſrael <hi>and</hi> Judah, <hi>which was grown exceeding great, the City being full of perverſneſs, and practical Atheiſme: For they ſtuck not to ſay, the Lord hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken the Earth; tuſh, God ſeeth not.</hi> Chap. 9.9. And for the <hi>Effects, London</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem, England</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> may ſhake <hi>hands,</hi> as <hi>v.</hi> 10. <hi>Quapropter etiam ego,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Therefore as for me alſo, ſaith the Lord, Mine eyes ſhall not ſpare, neither will I have pity; but I will recompenſe their way upon their head.</hi> And you will find, He did it much in the ſame manner, that He doth even now amongſt us: For the <hi>Six Executioners, v.</hi> 2. <hi>that He ſent forth with ſlaughtering weapons in their hands,</hi> they had a ſtrict charge and Commiſſion given them, <hi>v.</hi> 5, 6. <hi>to goe after the Man Cloathed in Linnen, with the Writers Inkhorn by his ſide, and kill and deſtroy all before them; Let not your eye ſpare,</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>neither have ye pity, but ſlay utterly old and young, both Maids and little Children, and women;</hi> and ſave none but onely thoſe that your <hi>Forerunner</hi> hath marked in their Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads: And thoſe were but a <hi>ſmall remnant</hi> that did ſeriouſly lay things to heart, and <hi>ſigh and mourn for all the abominations that were done among them, v.</hi> 4. Think I beſeech you upon
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:93632:9"/>this ſad <hi>Viſion,</hi> and I hope it may be an effectual means to to rouze and awake you all out of your ſinfull carnal ſecurity, and for the future make you <hi>Conſider; conſider</hi> (I mean) how the Caſe ſtands betwixt God and your own Souls; <hi>conſider</hi> your latter end, and the things that concern your <hi>eternal peace, leſt they be hid from your eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And then again,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Branch</hi> 2.</note> as it ſerves to reprove and condemn <hi>car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſecurity</hi> on the one hand; So on the other, to rebuke and correct that undue and dangerous affection of <hi>overmuch fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs and deſpondency,</hi> which too too many of both Sexes, but women eſpecially, are by nature inclinable to. 'Tis true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, our utmoſt <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Diſcretion,</hi> and all poſſible <hi>care</hi> is neceſſary both for the preventing, and for the avoyding of danger: But I know nothing more unſeaſonable, nor many times of more dangerous conſequence than a deſponding Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of Fear, and apprehenſive imagination. The effects whereof (as we all find by frequent experience and obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) ſtrangely ſometimes prove deſtructive and deadly to thoſe, which otherwiſe were placed (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) out of all probable reach of danger. Now if you inquire what may be the <hi>Cauſe,</hi> and what alſo the <hi>Cure</hi> of this unhappy <hi>Infirmity:</hi> I anſwer briefly; The Cauſe may be either,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1.<note place="margin">Cauſes of fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs.</note> A Natural inclination to <hi>Fearfulneſs:</hi> Or elſe,</item>
               <item>2. Want of Faith and Reſolution, becauſe people are not <hi>animo praeſenti,</hi> they do not carry their lives in their hands, that ſo they might be ready and willing to lay down the ſame, and chearfully reſign them up when God ſhal pleaſe: Or elſe,</item>
               <item>3. A conſciouſneſs to themſelves of their unfitneſs, and unpreparedneſs at preſent to dye, and to appear before God in Heaven: Or elſe,</item>
               <item>4. A dreadfull apprehenſion of the great pain and terror of death; and that perhaps as to the <hi>Manner</hi> and kind of death, as well as the <hi>Matter,</hi> their corporal diſſolution. Or laſtly,</item>
               <item>5. A frightfull foreſight, and ſelf-condemning Meditation upon that which enſues after Death, <hi>Judgement to come;</hi> the<note n="(h)" place="margin">Act. 24, 25.</note> 
                  <hi>reaſoning and diſcourſing whereof by St.</hi> Paul, <hi>made</hi> Felix <hi>trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</hi> Some or all theſe things before mentioned are, I conceive, the cauſes of this <hi>Paſſion</hi> in People.</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:93632:9"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Remedies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it.</note>And now for the perfect and certain Cure and remedy thereof, I know nothing in the whole world comparable to the due exerciſe of this great Duty of <hi>Conſideration.</hi> As</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. That there is nothing comes to paſs without the permiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and knowledge of God; nothing indeed befals us by chance; but the moſt caſual and accidental contingences, events and conſequences (howſoever we may think or judge of them) are over-ruled, and ſteered, and guided in a deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate manner by <hi>His Providence;</hi> which is the great <hi>Weight</hi> and Plumbet (as it were) that ſets and keeps all the <hi>Wheels</hi> a going, whether bigger or leſſer, in the vaſt <hi>Clock,</hi> the whole <hi>Fabrick of Nature:</hi> Inſomuch that nothing is done without it, not ſo much <hi>as a</hi>
               <note n="(i)" place="margin">Mat. 10.29, 30.</note> 
               <hi>ſparrow falls on the ground, no nor an hair from any of our heads without it.</hi> Now this one thought and conſideration naturally prompts us all to ſubmiſſion, and ſelf-reſignation, and alſo affords us matter of comfort and conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation. Firſt, it prompts us all to ſubmiſſion, foraſmuch as He is the great Creator and Governour of all things, <hi>the ever bleſſed and only Potentate,</hi> our Lord Paramount and abſolute Sovereign, whoſe we are by the right of Creation, Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Preſervation too. And therefore, if it be but civil and reaſonable (as we ſay) to give men leave to do what they will with their own; We may well be content to allow the ſame Priviledge to <hi>The Almighty,</hi> and reſt well ſatisfied with his good Will and Pleaſure in all things, <hi>Who</hi> knows far bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter what is good for us, than we our ſelves. Thus did <hi>David,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.18, 20. and likewiſe old <hi>Eli,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3. Where when he heard what terrible things were decreed againſt his houſe and poſterity, <hi>enough to make both the ears of every one that ſhould hear them, to tingle;</hi> (<hi>verſ.</hi> 11.) He neither repined nor murmured againſt it, but only ſaid like a meek good Man, <hi>Jehovah eſt; &amp;c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> is the Lord, let Him do what ſeemeth him good, verſ.</hi> 18. And thus laſtly did our Saviour, who though as Man, He could not but wiſh and pray that<note n="(k)" place="margin">Mat. 26.39, 42. Luk. 22.42.</note> 
               <hi>the bitter cup of his approaching Death and Paſſion might paſs from him,</hi> Yet <hi>Non mea, ſed fiat voluntas tua:</hi> (ſays He) <hi>not my will, but thy bleſſed will be done.</hi> And then ſecondly, it alſo affords us matter of comfort and conſolation, and that in the midſt and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:93632:10"/>worſt of tryals, or evils, that can befal us, or our Relations; inaſmuch as He is thorow <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> the <hi>Father of mercies,</hi> and hath graciouſly promiſed<note n="(l)" place="margin">Pſal. 145 9.</note> 
               <hi>that all things ſhall work toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for our good,</hi> and that <hi>he will never leave us nor forſake us. Love</hi> and <hi>Mercy</hi> (as the Pſalmiſt intimates) is ever more one Ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient in all his Diſpenſations towards us: Inſomuch that I dare deliver it for a <hi>certain Truth,</hi> though perhaps a <hi>ſeeming Paradox,</hi> that many times it is a mercy that God is pleaſed to remove and withdraw a mercy from us. For we may be ſure, if he take away one, it is that thereby He may make way for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, a greater and better to be beſtowed upon us. Thus He oft withdraws <hi>temporal Comforts,</hi> to make room in mens hearts for <hi>Spiritual Bleſſings</hi> and <hi>Graces;</hi> thus He oft denies health to our bodies, to make us mind the welfare of our ſouls; yea, thus He oft deprives his own dear Children and Servants of a <hi>natural life,</hi> that ſo He may take them unto Himſelf, and put them into a full and actual poſſeſſion of heavenly joys. The Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> averrs what I ſay; Chap. 57.1, 2. The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration whereof, I ſuppoſe, was that which enabled pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent <hi>Job</hi> ſo contentedly to entertain the moſt ſad news of the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain death of all his children;<note n="(m)" place="margin">Job 1.21.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord gave,</hi> &amp;c. This made <hi>David</hi> ſo chearfully ſay,<note n="(n)" place="margin">Pſal. 31.5.</note> 
               <hi>Into thine hands I commit my ſpirit,</hi> &amp;c. And this made<note n="(o)" place="margin">Phil. 1.21, 23.</note> St. <hi>Paul deſire to be diſſolved and to be with Chriſt,</hi> and to count <hi>death his exceeding gain.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain,</p>
            <p n="2">2. Another thought and conſideration that may be of very good uſe to arm and fortifie Believers againſt the affection of overmuch Fearfulneſs and Deſpondency,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Remedy</hi> 2.</note> is to conſider what Death is. Some indeed look upon it as <hi>Summa Malorum,</hi> the <hi>Worſt of all evils; Rex terrorum,</hi> the <hi>King of fears,</hi> and fancy it to be a moſt terrible <hi>fiery Serpent;</hi> but <hi>the</hi>
               <note n="(p)" place="margin">1 Cor. 15.56, 57.</note> 
               <hi>Sting,</hi> we know, <hi>is taken away;</hi> and then why, I pray you, ſhould it be ſo dreadful? In Scripture, I am ſure, it is called <hi>a ſleep, a</hi>
               <note n="(q)" place="margin">Job 3.17.</note> 
               <hi>cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from trouble;</hi> a <hi>reſting from labours;</hi> and ſo the Grave, a<note n="(r)" place="margin">Iſai. 57.2.</note> 
               <hi>bed to reſt in.</hi> Now what more grateful and welcome to Nature, when men are wearied and tired out with labour, than to betake themſelves to their reſt? What more comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able than a ſoft Bed? What more deſirable and pleaſant than
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:93632:10"/>ſleep? Nay, for ſome reaſons, in <hi>holy Writ,</hi> and by the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Fathers, it is very plainly preferred before life: For life (ſays St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) is nothing at all but <hi>tranſitus ad mortem,</hi> a paſſage to death; but <hi>Death</hi> is <hi>introitus in vitam meliorem,</hi> an Entrance into eternal life. This therefore, all things conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, muſt needs be better, as tending to a more excellent end. No wonder then that you hear St. <hi>John</hi>
               <note n="(s)" place="margin">Rev. 14.13.</note> pronounce <hi>them bleſſed that dye in the Lord.</hi> And good ground it ſeems had the <hi>Wiſeman</hi> to ſay,<note n="(t)" place="margin">Eccl. 7.1.</note> that <hi>the day of death is better than the day of ones birth;</hi> and Reaſon He had<note n="(u)" place="margin">Eccl. 4.2.</note> 
               <hi>to praiſe the dead, which are already dead, more than the living, which are yet alive.</hi> It is obſervable that the very Heathens were wont to celebrate the day of their <hi>Birth</hi> with ſadneſs, ſeriouſneſs, and ſorrow; but of a friends <hi>Death</hi> with all mirth, joyfulneſs, and feaſting: So fully and verily were they perſwaded of the truth of that memorable Saying of the Oracle, <hi>Optimam non naſci, proxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum mori;</hi> i. e. <hi>the beſt and moſt deſirable thing, is not to be born at all; the next, to dy quickly.</hi> Let none of us, I beſeech you therefore, fall ſhort of them in point of courage and reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; foraſmuch as <hi>our hope is not confined only to this life;</hi> for then indeed<note n="(w)" place="margin">1 Cor. 15.19.</note> 
               <hi>we were of all men moſt m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſerable:</hi> But we are aſſured of unſpeakable bliſs, and eternal peace in the life to come; and a joyful Reſurrection of our bodies at the laſt day. The <hi>Wiſeman</hi> tells us,<note n="(x)" place="margin">Eccl. 12.7.</note> that <hi>the Spirit ſhall return immediately unto God that gave it;</hi> and as for the <hi>Body, though it be laid in the duſt, and</hi>
               <note n="(y)" place="margin">1 Cor. 15.42, 43.</note> 
               <hi>ſown in corruption, yet it ſhall be raiſed in incorruption; though ſown in weakneſs, yet it ſhall raiſed in power; though ſown in diſhonour, yet it ſhall be raiſed in glory.</hi> Which Metaphorical phraſe of St. <hi>Paul</hi> gave the holy Fathers occaſion to call the <hi>Churchyard, Gods field upon earth:</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the <hi>graves</hi> are the <hi>furrows;</hi> the <hi>dead Bodies</hi> of his Saints are the <hi>Seeds</hi> ſown; and the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> at the laſt day, <hi>the time of harveſt,</hi> when God will ſend forth his <hi>Reapers,</hi> i.e. <hi>the holy Angels</hi> (as Chriſt himſelf expreſly<note n="(z)" place="margin">Mat. 13.39.</note> calls them) <hi>that they may</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">Mat. 24.31.</note> 
               <hi>gather his elect together from the four winds, and from the one end of heaven to the other, even as wheat into his gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</hi> And then,</p>
            <p n="3">3. Another <hi>conſideration</hi> is the impartiality of Death,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Remedy</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>when
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:93632:11"/>our appointed time is come,</hi> and the natural neceſſity of it: In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard whereof the Heathen<note n="(x)" place="margin">Horat. Ode <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> Poet ſays well, that <hi>aequo pede pulſat, pauperum tabernas, regum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> turres;</hi> i. e. <hi>It boldly knocks at the Palace gates of Princes and Nobles, as well as rings and raps at the doors of poor Peaſants.</hi> It balks nor ſpares none when it is ſent, be they high or low, rich or poor, young or old: For<note n="(b)" place="margin">Heb. 9.27.</note> 
               <hi>Statutum eſt,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>It is appointed for all men once to dye.</hi> Death is the greateſt Monarch, and the moſt ancient King in the world: For <hi>death</hi> (ſays<note n="(c)" place="margin">Rom. 5.14.</note> St. <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>hath reigned from Adam to Moſes;</hi> to which I may add, that it hath <hi>reigned from Moſes</hi> to us, and ſo ſhall ſtill <hi>reign over all</hi> to the end of the world. Every one without exception muſt ſtoop and bow to his Scepter. <hi>One</hi>
               <note n="(d)" place="margin">1 Cor. 15.41.</note> 
               <hi>ſtar indeed may differ from another ſtar in glory,</hi> i. e. in brightneſs, luſtre, and magnitude; but yet we know that as ſure as they have their Riſe in the Weſt, ſo ſure they are to ſet in the Eaſt: Even ſo, it's true, One man on earth may differ from another man in glory, <hi>i. e.</hi> in wiſedom, and wealth, or beauty and honour, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but yet notwithſtanding as ſure as they had a riſing in their <hi>Birth,</hi> ſo they ſhall have a ſetting in <hi>Death:</hi> the honour of the greateſt, as well as the meaneſt, when their appointed time is come, <hi>muſt be laid in the Duſt. For</hi>
               <note n="(e)" place="margin">Eccl. 2.15, 16.</note> 
               <hi>one event happens to them all; and how dyes the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man? even as the fool? Dye we muſt?</hi> (ſaid the<note n="(f)" place="margin">2 Sam. 14.14.</note> wiſe wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of <hi>Tekoah</hi>) <hi>neither doth God reſpect any perſon.</hi> Now ſeeing it is thus, that Death is ſo impartial and unavoidable, what greater folly, puſillanimity, and meanneſs of ſpirit can any man be guilty of than to be terrified with the thoughts of it? A far better courſe I am ſure it would be to fit and prepare our ſelves carefully for it. For then, as 'tis natural and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for all to dye, ſo it would be honourable and comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to them: Whereas, an unprofitable Fear of Death ſerves for no end that I can tell of, but only to render it dreadful and miſerable; and is ſo far from helping any ever a whit more to avoid and eſcape it, that it doth but rather haſten it upon them. But,</p>
            <p n="4">4. The laſt and principal conſideration is the thoughts of that moſt bleſſed and advantagious conſequence thereof;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Remedy</hi> 4.</note> I mean, <hi>that</hi>
               <note n="(g)" place="margin">Col. 1.2.</note> 
               <hi>inheritance of the Saints in light,</hi> that<note n="(h)" place="margin">2 Tim. 4.8.</note> 
               <hi>incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:93632:11"/>Crown of righteouſneſs;</hi> that<note n="*" place="margin">2 Cor. 4 17.</note> 
               <hi>far more exceeding and eternal weight of Glory,</hi> which we hope to be made partakers of hereafter in Heaven. <hi>For</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">2 Cor. 5.1.</note> 
               <hi>we know</hi> (ſays St. <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>that when our earthly houſe of this Tabernacle ſhall be diſſolved, we have a building of God, an houſe not made with hands, eternal in the Heavens.</hi> The conſideration whereof, one would think ſhould be enough to quell and ſuppreſs all inordinate fears of death, and rather indeed make it deſirable, than terrible to us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But that which keeps me ſo much in awe (will ſome perhaps plead) and makes my departure hence ſo terrible, is my unfitneſs and uncapableneſs at preſent of ſuch a bleſſed ſtate and condition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If you think ſo, and this be the Cauſe; Why do you not ſpeedily, and in good earneſt ſtrive to remove it? <hi>Ipſa morte nihil certius,</hi> &amp;c. that dye we muſt, there is nothing more certain; but as for the circumſtance of the <hi>Time</hi> when; the <hi>Place</hi> where; and the <hi>Manner</hi> how; there is nothing in the world more unknown, and by conſequence more uncertain: Why ſhould you then trifle away one minute more of your precious time, or neglect any good means that may tend to your Aſſurance? Conſider, I pray, that for this end chiefly it is that God lends you time, and affords you frequent oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities here in this world. And therefore the<note n="l" place="margin">Epheſ. 5.15, 16.</note> Apoſtles Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept is, <hi>See that you walk Circumſpectly, not as fools, but as wiſe, redeeming the time, becauſe the dayes are evil.</hi> And likewiſe St. <hi>Peters</hi> Exhortation;<note n="m" place="margin">2 Pet. 1.10.</note> 
               <hi>Wherefore, the rather <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rethren, give all diligence to make your calling, and Election ſure.</hi> And to the ſame purpoſe is that moſt pithy Prayer of the Pſalmiſt,<note n="n" place="margin">Pſal. 90.12.</note> 
               <hi>Lord teach us ſo to number our dayes, that we may apply our hearts unto Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom:</hi> Now,</p>
            <p>Doe but thus, and then to remove that laſt ground and Cauſe of Fear that was mentioned, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>thoughts of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to come,</hi> know for your comfort, that <hi>He</hi> that's appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted then to be <hi>Judge,</hi> is your <hi>Advocate</hi> and <hi>Mediator,</hi> and will appear for you as a friend and <hi>Compurgatour.</hi> Sometimes indeed He is called a<note n="*" place="margin">Revel. 5.5.</note> 
               <hi>Lion,</hi> and repreſented to us in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as a<note n="p" place="margin">Mal. 3.2.</note> 
               <hi>Refiner,</hi> nay ſometimes as<note n="q" place="margin">Heb. 12. <hi>ult.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>a conſuming fire</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the ungodly; but to the righteous, and true Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:93632:12"/>
               <hi>he</hi> will then be a <hi>Lamb,</hi> as <hi>He</hi> is ſtyled (for your comfort) in the<note n="r" place="margin">Revel 5.8.</note> 
               <hi>Apocalypſe;</hi> and as the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes him, he will manifeſt himſelf to them,<note n="s" place="margin">Iſa. 9.6.</note> as a moſt <hi>wiſe and wonderfull Redeemer, the everlaſting Father, the Prince of of Peace.</hi> So that they need not be afraid of that dreadful doom,<note place="margin">Math. 25.41.</note> 
               <hi>t Abite a me execrati,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Depart from me ye curſed;</hi> but may with confident hopes and aſſurance expect to hear that ſweet Abſolution and Invitation,<note n="*" place="margin">Ibid. v. <hi>34.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Adeſte benedicti patris mei, Come ye bleſſed Children of my Father, receive the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom prepared for you from the beginning of the World.</hi> And ſo much by way of Reprehenſion. Again,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>2</label> Is it ſo,<note place="margin">Of Exhortat.</note> 
               <hi>that when Gods judgments are in the Earth, and the ſad tokens of his diſpleaſure appear againſt a Perſon or Nation, then its a proper ſeaſon for them ſeriouſly to lay things to heart, and wiſely to conſider?</hi> I beſeech you then be exhorted to the Duty. And that none of you may be at a ſtand or loſs in your ſelves for want of fit matter to meditate upon, I ſhall here now reſume, and according to my promiſe, enlarge my ſelf to the full upon thoſe five forenamed Particulars,<note place="margin">The ſubject-matters of our Conſideration.</note> which I told you before in the Explication are the moſt proper ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject-matters of our <hi>Conſideration in the day of adverſity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">1. The Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction it ſelf.</note>1. <hi>The affliction it ſelf, the evil, diſaſter,</hi> or <hi>Viſitation what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever it be, that is befalne us.</hi> This muſt be ſeriouſly thought upon, and conſidered by us; that ſo by conſulting <hi>Gods holy Word,</hi> and by the help of his <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Spirit,</hi> we may come at laſt (as Himſelf<note n="†" place="margin">Micah 6.9.</note> requires) to underſtand the <hi>Voyce of Gods Rod,</hi> and the mind and meaning of <hi>Him that appointed it.</hi> Now the preſent <hi>Affliction,</hi> and <hi>ſore Viſitation,</hi> which we of this great and populous <hi>City,</hi> with the <hi>Places</hi> adjacent, and divers eminent <hi>Towns</hi> of this Nation do ſo ſadly groan and labour under, is that noyſom and deadly <hi>Epidemical diſeaſe</hi> of the <hi>Plague</hi> and <hi>Peſtilence.</hi> Concerning which, to help you a little in your <hi>Conſiderations</hi> upon it, I ſhall briefly ſubjoyn ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, 1. Touching the <hi>Names</hi> and <hi>Metaphorical Appellations</hi> that are aſſigned unto it in Scripture. And then 2. I ſhould likewiſe adde ſomething concerning the <hi>Nature of the Diſeaſe:</hi> But for this I referr you to the <hi>Philoſopher</hi> and the <hi>Phyſician,</hi> whoſe Art and Profeſſion doth oblige them to ſearch into, and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:93632:12"/>ſtudy the Nature both of this, and of all other bodily Mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies and Diſtempers. And I do it the rather, becauſe we ſhal finde enough in the <hi>Names</hi> to acquaint us with the foul <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> of it; which I heartily wiſh (if it be Gods will) that none of you that hear me this day may ever experimentally find, nor further underſtand than by the Names and Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters of it that you hear from others.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Scripture-names of the Plague.</note>1. The moſt uſual Name is that of <hi>Peſtis, quaſi Pereſtis</hi> (ſays the <hi>Etymologiſt</hi>) from the Verb <hi>Peredo,</hi> i. e. <hi>to eat through, or utterly to conſume and deſtroy.</hi> And thus it is called (as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive) from the contagious and moſt pernicious quality and property of it; which ſometimes hath been ſo extreamly vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, quick, and diffuſive, that we read of <hi>above fourteen thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand</hi> that once were deſtroyed by it <hi>in a moment,</hi> as you may ſee plainly, <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.45, 46, 49. and of <hi>three or four and twenty thouſand</hi> that dyed of it in the <hi>ſpace of a day,</hi> Numb. 25.9. with 1 Cor. 10.8. and afterwards of <hi>threeſcore and ten thouſand</hi> that periſhed by it in the <hi>ſpace of three dayes,</hi> 2 Sam. 24.15. Nay, of <hi>an hundred fourſcore and five thouſand,</hi> that were ſwept away by it in the ſpace of one night, as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 37.30.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A ſecond Name is that of <hi>Plaga</hi> (whence our <hi>Engliſh</hi> word <hi>Plague</hi>) which in <hi>Latine,</hi> we know, properly ſignifies a <hi>Stroak:</hi> to intimate to us, that where 'tis inflicted, it is as an angry <hi>Stroak</hi> of Gods wrath and vengeance upon a ſinful Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple or Nation. And hence it is alſo ſometimes called<note n="x" place="margin">Num. 11.33.</note> 
               <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſio,</hi> a <hi>ſmiting;</hi> ſometimes<note n="y" place="margin">Numb. 16.47. Pſal. 83.15, 16, 17.</note> 
               <hi>Vulneratio &amp; Conſternatio;</hi> i. e. <hi>a Conſternation and Wounding.</hi> Again,</p>
            <p n="3">3. A third Appellation given unto it, is that of <hi>Strages, Clades, &amp; Ruina;</hi> i. e. <hi>Ruine and Deſolation,</hi> (as S. <hi>Pag.</hi> and other <hi>Hebricians</hi> render the Original word in divers<note n="z" place="margin">Exod. 12.13. Zech. 14.12.</note> places) becauſe it ſo quickly <hi>conſumes</hi> (as the Prophet <hi>Zechariah</hi> ſpeaks) pulls down and demoliſheth theſe <hi>Earthly Tabernacles</hi> of our Bodies: And for the ſame reſpect and reaſon it is ſometimes termed even <hi>Ipſa Mors, Very Death,</hi> and <hi>Deſtruction</hi> it ſelf, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91.6.</p>
            <p>To theſe I might adde thoſe <hi>Periphraſtical Appellations</hi> in the ſaid Pſalm, <hi>of a terrour by night, and Gods Arrow that flyeth by day,</hi> verſ. 5. Where note by the way, that both for Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:93632:13"/>and our Preſervation too, the Pſalmiſt directs us to the moſt ſafe, and only ſure <hi>Refuge</hi> and <hi>Sanctuary, the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of the wings of the Almighty,</hi> v. 1, &amp; 4. and preſcribes the moſt ſovereign and only infallible <hi>Antidote</hi> in the whole world againſt the infection of the Plague, viz. <hi>Our ſole dependance and truſt in His great mercy and gracious protection,</hi> v. 9, 10. And therefore I think it a <hi>Pſalm</hi> fit and worthy to be diligently and daily read over, nay gotten by heart, and hourly medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated upon by all that hope and deſire to eſcape the contagion. For do but thou <hi>make the Lord thy refuge, and thy Fortreſs, and his Truth thy ſhield and buckler, and then thou needeſt not be afraid for the terrour by night, nor for the Arrow that flyeth by day. A thouſand ſhall fall at thy ſide, and ten thouſand at thy right hand; but it ſhall not come night thee. Becauſe thou haſt made the Lord, even the moſt High, thy habitation, there ſhal no evil befall thee; neither ſhal any Plague come nigh thy dwelling:</hi> How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, if thou eſcape not the <hi>Viſitation,</hi> yet thou ſhalt <hi>Gods in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation;</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 11.</note> 
               <hi>Who ſhall give his Angels charge over thee to keep thee in all thy ways,</hi> whileſt thou liveſt in this world; and at laſt to tranſport and conveigh thy Soul <hi>into Abrahams boſom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The deſtructive and deadly nature of it.</note>Theſe are the well-known uſual <hi>Names</hi> and <hi>Appellations</hi> aſſigned unto <hi>this Diſeaſe</hi> in Scripture. By which (as I inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated before) you may eaſily judge of the deſtructive, foul <hi>Nature</hi> of it. But if what hath been ſpoken be not ſufficient to repreſent <hi>that</hi> to the full unto you; give me leave then to minde you of ſome emphatical Phraſes in Scripture, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Gods inflicting of this fore Judgement is expreſſed by the Holy Ghoſt. Sometimes it is expreſſed by <hi>cauſing his anger and jealouſie to ſmoak againſt a Perſon or Nation, and by ſeparating them unto evil,</hi> as <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.20, 21, 22. and 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 34.25. Sometimes <hi>by heaping miſchiefs, and ſpending his arrows upon them, and devouring them with bitter deſtruction,</hi> as Deut. 32.23, 24, 25. Sometimes by <hi>laying his hand very heavy upon them, and ſending a deadly deſtruction amongſt them,</hi> as 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 5.11. Sometimes <hi>by making men-drink the wrath of the Almighty,</hi> as <hi>Job</hi> 21.20. and <hi>the Wormwood-wine of trouble and aſtoniſhment,</hi> as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 60.3. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.8. And ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <hi>by perſecuting them with his tempeſts, and making them
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:93632:13"/>afraid with his ſtorms,</hi> as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 83.15. No wonder then, that <hi>Almighty God</hi> reckons <hi>this as one of his four moſt</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Ezek 14.21.</note> 
               <hi>ſore judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> that he ſometimes <hi>ſends upon a rebellions City or Kingdom.</hi> And ſo much for the firſt particular ſubject-matter of our <hi>Conſideration, the Affliction it ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Second was the <hi>Diſpenſer</hi> and <hi>Author</hi> of it:<note place="margin">2. The Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer of it.</note> And primarily and principally that ſtill is <hi>God,</hi> who does it for our good. <hi>For</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Amos 3.6. Ruth 1.21. Iſa. 45.7.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall there be evil in a City, and the Lord hath not done it?</hi> No; <hi>Mihi Vindicta: Vengeance is mine,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Deut. 32.35. Rom. 12.19.</note> 
               <hi>I will repay, ſaith the Lord.</hi> It was the fault of <hi>King Aſa,</hi> (2 Chron. 16.12.) <hi>that in his diſeaſe he ſought not unto the Lord, but to the Phyſicians.</hi> But we muſt acknowledge a <hi>Digitus Dei,</hi> The <hi>finger of God</hi> in this preſent ſad <hi>Viſitation</hi> above and before all other natural and ſecondary Cauſes, and look up eſpecially unto Him; or elſe we are guilty of the ſame Crime. Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, <hi>there is no evil</hi> (as <hi>Job</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Job 5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> intimates) <hi>but it is a ſpark of Gods wrath.</hi> But in this of the <hi>Plague, Gods anger</hi> ſeems to be <hi>kindled,</hi> as<note n="*" place="margin">Numb. 25.3.</note> 
               <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpeaks; and thoſe <hi>ſparks of his wrath to be blown up,</hi> as it were, <hi>into a flame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>The third was the ground,</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. The ground and cauſe of it.</note> 
               <hi>or the procuring and meritorious Cauſe of it.</hi> And for this we muſt, look into our own hearts, examine our ſelves, and <hi>conſider our wayes,</hi> as being well aſſured and convinced of this one thing in general beforehand, <hi>That it is ſin, and nothing but ſin that doth withhold</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Jer. 5.25. &amp; <hi>ch.</hi> 13.22. &amp; <hi>ch.</hi> 16.10, 11, 12, 13.</note> 
               <hi>good things from us,</hi> and which is the Cauſe of all the Evils, Afflictions, and Miſeries that do befall us. More particularly, the <hi>Grounds and Cauſes</hi> of this moſt dreadfull noyſom Diſeaſe that we labour under, are of two ſorts: Either 1. Such as rationally are ſuppoſed, and probably aſſigned by the Philoſopher, and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily Phyſicion, I mean thoſe external natural Cauſes, which are briefly ſumm'd up in the <hi>ſeaſonable. Exhortation</hi> anneked to the <hi>Form of Prayer</hi> for this day. Or elſe, 2. Such as unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly are agreed on by all, and certainly determined by the <hi>Divine,</hi> and <hi>Gods holy Word:</hi> I mean thoſe internal and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernatural Cauſes of our own <hi>Sins</hi> and <hi>Provocations,</hi> and Gods juſt <hi>wrath and indignation</hi> thereupon: Both which are mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and layd down by the Pſalmiſt as the ſole Cauſes of that ſodain, Plague which befell the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> for their Idolatry and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:93632:14"/>Fornication with the <hi>Midianites: For thus</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 106.29. with Num. 25.3.</note> 
               <hi>they provoked the Almighty to anger with their Inventions, and ſo the Plague brake in upon them.</hi> And yet it is not ſo much for <hi>Sin</hi> in general, as rather for ſome hainous and horrid ſins in particular, that Gods wrath and anger is thus kindled againſt any people. In my recounting and diſcovering of which, I ſhall (God willing) uſe all faithfulneſs and impartiality without fear or favour: for which end, I ſhall not truſt to mine own private judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, nor yet follow the partial Opinions, and cenſorious Fancies of others; who being byaſſed by their affections and inclinations, their novel and corrupt Principles and Perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, their ſelf-love and intereſt, are ready hypocritically and ſubtilly to juſtifie themſelves, but politickly and maliciouſly to caſt all the <hi>Odium</hi> they can upon others: And hence it is, that you hear ſome mutter and murmure, that it is for the <hi>Sins of the Court</hi> eſpecially, that this fore Judgement is layd upon us: Others whiſper, that the fault is chiefly in the <hi>Biſhops and Clergy;</hi> who have neither the <hi>Way</hi> nor <hi>Faculty</hi> themſelves to pleaſe the generality of the people by their Preaching and Divine Service, nor yet will permit others, whom they could fancy, to exerciſe their Gifts in their Churches and Pulpits: And a third ſort cry out, that it is becauſe they are perſecuted (as they pretend) and are not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered as in the late <hi>Olivarian dayes,</hi> to enjoy their beloved <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Conſcience,</hi> as they call it: I ſhall not tread in the ſteps of theſe <hi>Perſons</hi> or <hi>Parties,</hi> and with them poſitively and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptorily conclude and determine, that this or that parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular <hi>thing,</hi> theſe or thoſe <hi>Perſons</hi> are the <hi>provoking and merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Cauſes</hi> of our unparallel'd <hi>Viſitation;</hi> but to prevent all miſtakes and errours in ſo nearly concerning an Inquiry and Diſcovery, I ſhall ſteer my courſe by the <hi>Compaſs</hi> only of <hi>Gods holy Word,</hi> and make <hi>that</hi> alone my Conduct and Pilot un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till we be paſt theſe moſt dangerous ſhelves and quick ſands.</p>
            <p>In Scripture then, where the ſacred Pen-men are never found to balk either themſelves or others; but, quite cont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the humour of many in theſe our dayes, that think ſo highly and well of themſelves, are alwayes wont faithfully to record and reveal, yea even aggravate, rather than conceal
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:93632:14"/>and extenuate the groſſeſt Errours and C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> of thoſe, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Princes, Prophets, Prieſts or People that have provoked the Almighty to wrath (ſtudying it ſeems moſt of all to give due honour and glory to <hi>Gods holy Name,</hi> howſoever they took ſhame to themſelves). In Scripture, I ſay, I find even <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Princes</hi> themſelves arraigned at the <hi>Barre of Gods Juſtice</hi> as well as their <hi>Subjects;</hi> and ſometimes the blame layd upon the one, and ſometimes upon the other (<hi>for</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Acts 10.34.</note> 
               <hi>He is no reſpecter of Perſons</hi>) for provoking the Lord by ſome ſpecial ſins to inflict this ſore Judgement upon his People: And yet neither of them pleading Non-guilty to the Accuſation and Charge drawn up againſt them by the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> but confeſſing their Crimes, and humbling themſelves in duſt and aſhes, that by Prayer and Faſting they might obtain pardon.</p>
            <p>The ſpecial Sins mentioned in Scripture,<note place="margin">Sins of Princes that have oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned the Plague.</note> whereby Kings and Princes have provoked God to pour out the Vials of his wrath in this manner, they are only two, to my beſt remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, <hi>Pride,</hi> and <hi>Blaſphemy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Pride of heart,</hi> which was <hi>Davids</hi> Offence, as 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24. with 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 21.1. where you will finde, that through Vain glory, and Satans inſtigation, <hi>his heart was lifted up to number Iſrael: but God was diſpleaſed with this thing</hi> (ſays the Text, <hi>v.</hi> 7.) <hi>and therefore He ſmote Iſrael with a violent Plague, which in three dayes deſtroyed threeſcore and ten thouſand.</hi> It is likewiſe the judgement of St. <hi>Jerom, Cyril,</hi> and <hi>Theodoret</hi> (as <hi>A Lapide</hi> notes) that to prevent, if not chaſtiſe this ſame dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Principle of Pride in King <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> which probably he might be inclinable to, and guilty of, upon the conceit and conſideration of that miraculous happy deliverance of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> from the force and fury of the King of <hi>Aſſyria;</hi> when for his ſake, and upon his effectual Prayers and Tears, there were near upon two hundred thouſand of the Enemies Army<note n="*" place="margin">Iſa. 37.14, to <hi>v.</hi> 36.</note> deſtroyed in one night; their judgement is, that (as ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time a<note n="k" place="margin">2 Cor. 12.7.</note> 
               <hi>Thorn in the fleſh, the Meſſenger of Satan was ſent to St.</hi> Paul, <hi>to buffet him, leſt he ſhould have been exalted above meaſure, through the abundance of revelations;</hi> even ſo) the Lord was pleaſed to viſit King <hi>Hezekiah</hi> perſonally with this very <hi>Sickneſs;</hi> Iſai. 38.1, 21. And yet all, it ſeems, ſcarely enough:
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:93632:15"/>for afterwards <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd it got vent, though its true upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther occaſion, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as he pretended out of civility and cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie to ſtrangers, rather than any oſtentation in himſelf, as <hi>Chap.</hi> 39.1, 2, 4.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Blaſphemy;</hi> and this was the black and provoking Sin of the aforeſaid <hi>King of Aſſyria, Senacherib</hi> I mean, and his compliant foul-mouthed Servant and eloquent Orator, <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Rabſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>keh:</hi> whoſe breath ſo forcibly blew up the coals of <hi>Gods</hi> anger, that it preſently made his <hi>jealouſie burn like fire,</hi> and conſume ſo many thouſands of their Men in one night. Theſe are the two only ſpecial Sins (as I remember) mentioned in Scripture, whereby Kings and Princes have provoked God to pour out the vials of his wrath in this manner. But ſure I am, that we of this Nation, have not the leaſt ground or oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to ſuſpect or imagine that our <hi>Dread Sovereign</hi> ſhould be guilty of either of them; <hi>Who</hi> hath purchaſed the Name and Reputation abroad in the world, and alſo approved <hi>Himſelf</hi> here at home, to be both a very wiſe, and moſt rarely accompliſhed <hi>Perſon,</hi> as to his natural Parts and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments; and alſo as to his ſpiritual Gifts and Inclinations, a truly religious, meek, and moſt gracious, merciful <hi>Prince;</hi> in ſhort, <hi>a good man as well as a great Monarch:</hi> And therefore we may very well acquit and exonerate Him from all guilt, as to theſe great and capital Sins; and ſo by conſequence, from the foul Cenſure of being eminently acceſſory to the ſore Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation that we now labour under.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Sins of people that have cauſed the Plague.</note>The ſpecial and particular Sins mentioned in Scripture, whereby common People, I mean, the mixt Multitude, and Body Politick of a Nation, have provoked God to pour out the vials of his wrath in this manner upon them, are diverſe: I ſhall firſt name them and ſet them in order before your eyes, by referring you to thoſe plain and expreſs portions of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, where I find them recorded; and then afterwards bring home our Diſcourſe in a brief application unto our ſelves. They are ſix in number.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Wilful diſobedience, and a general Apoſtacy from the true God, and his holy Laws and Commandements.</hi> This is clear from <hi>Deu.</hi> 28.15, 20, 21. <hi>It ſhall come to paſs, if thou wilt not hearken
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:93632:15"/>unto the voyce of the Lord thy God, to do all his Commandements and his Statutes,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>that then the Lord ſhall ſend upon thee cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, vexation, and rebuke in all that thou ſetteſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hine hand unto for to do, until thou be deſtroyed, and periſh quickly; the Lord ſhall make the Peſtilence cleave unto thee, untill He have conſumed thee;</hi> So <hi>Levit.</hi> 26.21, 22. &amp;c. <hi>If ye walk contrary unto me, and will not hearken unto me, I will bring ſeven times more Plagues upon you, according to your ſins,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And if ye will not be reformed by theſe things, but will ſtill walk contrary unto me, then will I alſo walk contrary unto you, and will puniſh you yet ſeven times for your ſins,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And when ye are gathered together within your Cities, I will fend the Peſtilence among you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Flat obſtinacy, and open rebellion againſt lawful Magiſtrates, the higher Powers, that God hath ſet over us:</hi> Which the Apoſtle tells us is no leſs than <hi>to</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Rom. 13.2.</note> 
               <hi>reſiſt the Ordinance of God;</hi> and <hi>they that do ſo ſhall hereafter receive to themſelves Damnation:</hi> No wonder then, that at preſent here <hi>this dreadful Judgment</hi> of the Plague and Peſtilence be threatned by God againſt all ſuch <hi>children of Diſobedience;</hi> as indeed it is, <hi>Numb.</hi> 14.2, 3, 4. with <hi>verſ.</hi> 11, 12. <hi>Where when the Children of Iſrael murmured againſt Moſes and Aaron, and ſaid unto them, Would God that we had dyed in the land of Egypt, or in this Wilderneſs: Wherefore hath the Lord brought us unto this land to fall by the ſword, that our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ives and our children ſhould be a prey? Were it not better for us to return into Egypt? And they ſaid one to another, Let us make a Captain, and let us return into Egypt. Hereupon the Lord ſaid unto Moſes, How long will this people provoke me? I will ſmite them with the Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and will diſinherit them, and will make of thee a greater N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and mightier than they.</hi> And as it was threatned in this Chapter for this <hi>ſeditious murmuring and conſpiracy;</hi> ſo it was actually inflicted upon ſome in the ſixteenth Chapter, <hi>viz.</hi> fourteen thouſand and ſeven hundred of thoſe Abetters and Favourers of the Rebellion of <hi>Korah, Dathan, and Abiram,</hi> as verſ. 41. to the end of the Chapter. For the proof of this I might likewiſe refer you to <hi>Jer.</hi> 27.8. with Chap. 21.6, 9. which you may pleaſe to peruſe at leaſure.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>A pertinacious reſiſtance of thoſe regular and faithful Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, thoſe ſpiritual Labourers in Chriſts Vineyard, which by
<pb facs="tcp:93632:16"/>Gods Providence are ſent amongſt them: Peoples ſlighting, deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, reviling and reproaching of theſe, and like the deaf Adder ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping their ears to the voyce of theſe Charmers let them charm never ſo wiſely:</hi> and on the contrary, running after falſe Prophers, and <hi>becauſe they will not endure ſound Doctrine</hi> (as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">2 Tim. 4.3, 4.</note> Prophecies plainly of them) <hi>afeer their own luſts heaping to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves teachers of their own (not of Gods I am ſure) having itch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ears.</hi> Now for this, the Plague and other ſore Judgements are threatned by God; as <hi>Jer.</hi> 29.15, 17, 18, 19. <hi>Becauſe ye have ſaid, the Lord hath raiſed us up Prophets in Babylon: Thus ſaith the Lord of Hoſts: Behold I will ſend upon them the Sword the Famine, and the Peſtilence, and will make them like vile figs that cannot be eaten they are ſo evil. And I will perſecute them with the Sword, with the Famine, and with the Peſtilence, and will deliver them to be removed to all the Kingdoms of the earth, to be a curſe, and an aſtoniſhment, and an hiſſing, and a reproach among all the Nations, whither I have driven them: Becauſe they have not hearkened to my words, ſaith the Lord, which I ſent unto them by my ſervants the Prophets, riſing up early, and ſending them; but ye would not hear, ſaith the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>The ſlighting of the Ordinances of God, and particularly the neglect, or at leaſt profanation of and abuſing the holy Sacrament of the Lords Supper:</hi> Which St. <hi>Paul</hi> looks upon as the Cauſe of the <hi>ſickneſs</hi> and <hi>Viſitation</hi> that happened to the Believers at<note n="n" place="margin">1 Cor. 11.30.</note> 
               <hi>Corinth.</hi> Many it ſeems were come to that paſs (as they are even now in theſe days) that they cared not whether they came or no unto that Sacrament; or at leaſtwiſe they came they cared not how. And therefore (ſays He) <hi>for this Cauſe many are weak and ſickly among you, yea, and many are fallen aſleep.</hi>
               <q>And this is no new thing, ſays the <hi>Right reverend Father in God, Biſhop</hi> Andrews: <hi>Moſes</hi> himſelf ſuffer'd for this; <hi>His</hi> neglect of the Sacrament of <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> to be adminiſtred to his Child (out of compliance with his tender-hearted, or if you will, peeviſh Wife <hi>Zipporah</hi>) made God to meet him in great anger by the way in the Inne, and it was like to have coſt him his life, <bibl>
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 4.24, 25, 26.</bibl>
               </q> The remembrance whereof made him preferr that petition to <hi>Pharaoh,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Exod. 5.3.</note> 
               <hi>Let us go, we pray thee, three days journey into the Wilderneſs, and there
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:93632:16"/>ſacrifice unto the Lord our God; leſt otherwiſe,</hi> if we neglect our own duty, and ſlight his due worſhip and ſervice, <hi>He fall upon us with the Peſtilence, or with the Sword:</hi> which it ſeems they might very juſtly fear, <q>in regard that the Sacrament of the <hi>Paſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>over,</hi> and the blood of it was the means to ſave them and their Families from the Plague of the deſtroying Angel in <hi>Egypt,</hi>
               </q> as you may ſee <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.13.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>That provoking and unpardonable Sin of Idolatry:</hi> as you ſhall find <hi>Ezek.</hi> 5.11, 12, &amp; 17. <hi>As I live, ſaith the Lord God, Surely becauſe thou haſt defiled my Sanctuary with all thy deteſtable things, and with all thine abomin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ons; therefore will I alſo dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh thee, neither ſhall mine eye ſpare, neither will I hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pity. A third part of thee ſhall dye with the Peſtilence, and with Famine ſhall they be conſumed,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Thus ſhall mine anger be accompliſhed, and I will cauſe my fury to reſt upon thee,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>For I will ſend upon thee Famine, and evil Beaſts, and they ſhall bereave thee, and Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and Blood ſhall paſs thorow thee.</hi> So again, Chap. 6.5, 6, 7. <hi>I will lay the dead carcaſes of the children of Iſrael before their Idols, and I will ſcatter your bones round about your Altars,</hi> &amp;c</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>The laſt is that beaſtly Sin of fornication and u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cleanneſs.</hi> For which, as we ſometimes<note n="p" place="margin">Gen. 19 24.25. with Deut. 29.23.</note> read that four eminent Cities were deſtroyed <hi>by Fire and Brimſtone from heaven,</hi> v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>z. <hi>Sodom, Gomorrah, Admah,</hi> and <hi>Zeboim,</hi> and the whole <hi>plain-Country</hi> turned into a ſtanding ſtinking Lake, called <hi>The Dead Sea</hi> to this day; So afterwards, when the <hi>Children of Iſrael joyning themſelves unto Beal Peor</hi> were grown to that height of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and impudence, as to commit it openly with <hi>the Daughters of Moab and Midian,</hi> this grievous judgement of the Plague and Peſtilence was inflicted upon them for it; as you may ſee, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.28, 29. and more fully <hi>Numb.</hi> 25.1, 2, to verſ. 10. <q>A proper puniſhment (ſays my Reverend Author) for ſo heinous a provocation, ſeeing the foul ſin of fornication commonly ends in ſores and ulcers, which are as infections as the Plague it ſelf.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe ſix, I think, are all the ſpecial and particular Sins mentioned in Scripture, whereby common People, I mean the mixt Multi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ude and Body Politick of a Nation have provoked God to pour out the Vials of his wrath and fury in this manner
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:93632:17"/>upon them. Now <hi>ſeeing that</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Rom. 15.4. &amp; 1 Cor. 10.6.</note> 
               <hi>whatſoever things were written aforetime were written for our learning;</hi> and that <hi>theſe things are our examples, to the end that we ſhould not tempt and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke God, as others have done,</hi> by the commiſſion of theſe groſs ſins, to infflict this moſt <hi>dreadful Judgment</hi> upon us: But yet foraſmuch as Gods anger hath been of late, and ſtill is ſtretched out againſt us this way in an extraordinary ſevere manner; We may therefore be ſure, that it is for ſome or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the aforeſaid iniquities which we of this ſinful Nation in general, and this populous City in particular, epidemical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, my meaning is, for the major part ſtand guilty of, that this unpa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>llel'd and ſore <hi>Viſitation</hi> is laid upon us. To expiate which, Oh that there were ſuch truly ingenuous, tender, and honeſt hearts in every one of us, that in our Confeſſions and Deprecations we might deal as faithfully and impartially betwixt God and our own Souls, as the <hi>ſacred Penmen of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> have done in declaring the ſins and provocations of Gods people, and His ſevere puniſhments and <hi>Judgments</hi> upon them for the ſame. <hi>For</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">1 Cor. 10.11.</note> 
               <hi>all thoſe things happened unto the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples; and they are written for our admonition, upon whom the ends of the world are come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Authors opinion, why this ſore judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is now laid upon us.</note>If any of you expect and deſire that I ſhould here now declare my Opinion, for which of the forementioned ſins I conceive it is, that this <hi>ſore Judgment</hi> is laid upon us; (though I know ſuch deſires are commonly made out of deſign, that people may know how to affect and fancy the Preacher, yet) I ſhall not ſcruple very briefly, and plainly to give you my judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>viz.</hi> That I do not think that it is for ends or that one <hi>Sin</hi> in particular, but rather for them all. As it's true with St. <hi>James, That</hi>
               <note n="s" place="margin">Jam. 3.2.</note> 
               <hi>in many things we offend all;</hi> ſo here it may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo as truly be ſaid, <hi>that in all theſe things, I mean the forenamed Capital Crimes, we offend too too many.</hi> For which of the ſix can we inſtance in, of which there are not many amongſt us that muſt needs confeſs themſelves guilty? Give me leave to make ſome ſhort reflections upon them ſeverally, and then I ſhall leave you all to judge. Now in this diſquiſition I ſhall obſerve a retrograde Motion, beginning with that which I ended with, when I named them before, that ſo <hi>the firſt may be laſt, and the laſt may be firſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:93632:17"/>
            <p n="1">1. In the firſt place then, for <hi>the foul Sin of Fornication and uncleanneſs;</hi> may not Almighty God bring the ſame charge againſt many, very many of this City and Nation, that He ſometimes brought againſt the inhabitants of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and many of the Jews?<note n="t" place="margin">Jer. 5, 7, 8, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>When I had fed them to the full, they then committed adultery, and aſſembled themſelves by troops in the harlots houſes: they were as fed Horſes in the morning, every one neighed after his Neighbours wife.</hi> And what then follows? <hi>Now, how ſhall I pardon thee for this? Shall I not viſit for theſe things, ſaith the Lord, and ſhall not my ſoul be avenged on ſuch a Nation as this?</hi> And then</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, for <hi>that provoking and unpardonable Sin of Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry.</hi> You muſt know it is twofold: either <hi>viſible and external</hi> in reference to the <hi>Body,</hi> or elſe <hi>ſpiritual and internal</hi> in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the <hi>Soul.</hi> Now, though I hope and believe that there are few or none amongſt us ſo notoriouſly wicked as to be guilty of the former; I mean, to contrive and make to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>graven Images,</hi> and then fall down and worſhip them as <hi>Gods,</hi> (unleſs it be ſome of the moſt wretched and groſſeſt ſort of Papiſts) yet I doubt there are too too many amongſt us guilty of the latter, <hi>ſpiritual and internal Idolatry.</hi> For you muſt note,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That <hi>that</hi> is every mans <hi>God</hi> or <hi>Idol,</hi> which his heart is moſt of all ſet upon. Now, if it be not the only true God, but wrong objects, he is <hi>ipſo facto</hi> guilty of <hi>Idolatry.</hi> Thus the ſottiſh <hi>Winebibber,</hi> and gluttonous <hi>Epicure</hi> may be juſtly called <hi>Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> becauſe <hi>they</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Phil. 3.19.</note> 
               <hi>make their belly their God;</hi> but<note n="†" place="margin">Iſai. 5.12.</note> 
               <hi>they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard not the works of the Lord, neither conſider the operations of his hands.</hi> Thus alſo the wretched <hi>Worldling,</hi> and covetous <hi>Mammoniſt,</hi> who<note n="x" place="margin">Job 31.24.</note> 
               <hi>maketh gold his hope,</hi> and <hi>truſteth in the multitude of his riches,</hi> is a plain <hi>Idolater</hi> (as the Apoſtle<note n="y" place="margin">Col. 3.5.</note> calls him) becauſe he makes an Idol of his wealth. And thus laſtly, <hi>He that truſteth in man more than in God,</hi> is a meer <hi>Idolater</hi> and accurſed before God, becauſe <hi>he</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Jer. 17.5.</note> 
               <hi>maketh fleſh his arm, and his heart departeth from the Lord.</hi> And then</p>
            <p n="2">2. To think amiſs, and otherwiſe of God than He is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented unto us in his holy Word, this again is <hi>Idolatry;</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Quia ſculp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile &amp; conſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le reor dogmata eſſe perverſa, quae ab his qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus facta ſunt adorantur, <hi>Hier.</hi>
               </note> Becauſe a perverſe and wicked opinion of God is no leſs then
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:93632:18"/>a graven Image, ſays St. <hi>Jerome.</hi> And therefore both he and St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> agree, that <hi>Uſque hodie in Templo Dei,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>i. e.</hi> even to this very day there are many amongſt us that ſet up Idols in the Church of God, when men in their hearts &amp; minds conceive and feign and new, erroneous, and unworthy opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, eſpecially concerning the Perſons of the <hi>bleſſed Trinity.</hi> Now, whether many amongſt us may not be thought guilty <hi>of this kind of Idolatry</hi> is eaſie to imagine: And then let ſuch know, that they cannot clear nor acquit themſelves from ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a hand in pulling down this preſent heavy Judgement upon us.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, <hi>For ſlighting and contemning the Ordinances of Chriſt, and particularly the Neglect, or at leaſt profanation of and abuſing the Sacrament of the Lords Supper:</hi> Never was Generation of men profeſſing Chriſtianity, in any Age or part of the world more guilty of this, than thoſe that ſtill are, and of late years have been the greateſt Pretenders to extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Zeal and Devotion, ſtrictneſs and Reformation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us. And hence it is, that when Times and Dayes are ſolemnly appointed for the celebration of that Sacrament; though ſerious warnings, and earneſt Exhortations are uſed by us the Miniſters of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> to perſwade and prepare people for a worthy, a comfortable, and a frequent partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of the <hi>ſacred Elements</hi> there exhibited, <hi>viz.</hi> the bleſſed <hi>Body and Blood of Chriſt;</hi> yet you ſhall finde few or none of that Faction and party affording their preſence: As if they had never read nor heard of, or at leaſt were reſolved not to believe nor regard thoſe words of our Saviour;<note n="b" place="margin">Joh. 6, 53, 54, 55.</note> 
               <hi>Verily, verily I ſay unto you, except ye eat the fleſh of the Son of man, and drink his blood, ye have no life in you. Whoſo eateth my fleſh, and drinketh my blood, hath eternal life, and I will raiſe him up at the laſt day. For my fleſh is meat indeed, and my blood is drink indeed.</hi> Which words, and whole Chapter, I wonder how they can read with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out horrour and aſtoniſhment, when they conſider and call to minde how irregularly they walk, and directly contrary both to the expreſs <hi>Precept</hi> of Chriſt, and alſo the apparent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant <hi>Practice</hi> of the Apoſtles themſelves, and the Saints and Martyrs of the Church in all Ages. And if ſuch as theſe,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:93632:18"/>who have gotten the name and reputation of <hi>Religious and ſtrict walk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs,</hi> be thus obſtinate, and ſo exceeding faulty in this point: then what can be looked for from many others vicious, looſe, and prophane in their lives, but that, as we find, they ſhould either plead the others example for their abſence from, and neglect of this Sacrament; or elſe, as we fear, preſumptuouſly approach the <hi>Lords Table</hi> with unprepared and unſanctified hearts and hands; to the great diſhonour and profanation of <hi>Gods holy Ordinance,</hi> and the <hi>damnation</hi> of their own ſouls? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.29. Again,</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>For that pertinacious Reſiſtance of thoſe regular and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Miniſters, thoſe ſpiritual Labourers in Chriſts Vin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yard which by Gods Providence are ſent forth; for Peoples ſlighting, reviling, deſpiſing and reproaching of theſe, and on the contrary, running after falſe Prophets, as I ſaid before;</hi> that too too many are guilty of this, may eaſily be ſeen every Lords-day, every Faſt, and Feſtival-day, when, if it be known (I am aſhamed and even tremble to ſpeak it) that there is like to be nothing at Church but only that which is purely divine, <hi>viz. Gods holy Word</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly read, and our moſt excellent <hi>publick Prayers and pithy Ejaculations</hi> devoutly poured out at the throne of Gods grace, for our ſelves, for our Sovereign and his Kingdoms; for Grace, Mercy, and Pardon of ſin, with Peace and Proſperity: Or if it be known, that the Miniſter hath a <hi>Set-form of Prayer,</hi> and makes uſe of his <hi>Notes</hi> in his preaching; then you ſhall ſcarcely have more of one <hi>Party</hi> (whoſe <hi>Prejudice</hi> and <hi>Fancy</hi> is above their <hi>Reaſon, Religion,</hi> and <hi>Conſcience</hi>) than Stone-pillars to make their apperance for that time. But let infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on and notice be given that ſome <hi>Stentorean</hi> fam'd Non-Conformiſt, ſome popular and newly cryed-up Preacher, that ſeems to pray without premeditat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on, and preacheth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out book, never looking upon Notes nor Bible: One that will neither uſe himſelf, nor trouble them with <hi>the Prayers of the Church,</hi> but entertain them only with <hi>a Pſalm, a Prayer of his own extemporary Effuſion,</hi> and a pleaſing, plauſible diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, concerning a <hi>ſtrict and cloſe walking with God, the illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations and inward operations of the Spirit of Grace, an Intereſt in Chriſt and the New Covenant,</hi> &amp;c. And withall, in his Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:93632:19"/>will declaim with a great deal of zeal, affection and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemency againſt thoſe ſins which our Superiours in Church and State, or others in general, that are not of the ſame ſtrain and opinion with himſelf, are uſually cenſured and ſuppoſed to be moſt guilty of, (which is an effectual, fine ſubtile way, to beget diſaffection, and ſow the ſeeds of ſedition in peoples hearts towards their Governours, as alſo to beget inward heart-burnings in them, with cenſoriouſneſs, diviſions, and uncharitableneſs towards their brethren:) Let it, I ſay, be but noyſed, nay whiſpered abroad that ſuch a one is to <hi>teach</hi> in this or that place, either Morning or Afternoon; and then though the Church were as large as <hi>St. Pauls,</hi> yet it will ſcarcely find room enough to receive and contain the diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly Rabble of his ſequacious eager followers. You all I believe, know and obſerve this to be true; and many per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps think it no crime, but rather commendable, in regard it is ſo cuſtomary and ordinary; yea the principal Thing that is now in faſhion, as to Religion, as being the chief and only means (this ſlighting of Prayers, and running after Sermons) to gain one the <hi>Name and Reputation of a Religious, godly Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</hi> But had I time to diſcover unto you the miſchievous and unhappy <hi>Effects and Conſequences</hi> of it, and that as well in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of <hi>the Publick,</hi> as of mens own <hi>Souls and Conſciences,</hi> in regard it is <hi>this</hi> that begets heart-burnings and animoſities amongſt Chriſtian Neighbours (as I hinted before) with divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, cenſurings, and uncharitableneſs each unto others; it's <hi>this</hi> that breeds and feeds, and foments that cauſeleſs diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and diſaffection in peoples Hearts towards their Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours; it's <hi>this</hi> that kindles the firſt ſparks of ſedition, diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, and Rebellion againſt lawfull Magiſtrates, which are ready to break out into a flame, when opportunity offers it ſelf; it's apparently <hi>this</hi> that makes people ſo <hi>unſetled in judgement,</hi> and<note n="c" place="margin">Jam. 1.8.</note> 
               <hi>unſtable in all their wayes,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">2 Tim. 3.7.</note> 
               <hi>ever learning, but never able to come to the knowledge of the truth;</hi> in a word, it is <hi>this,</hi> that makes many<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibid. v.</hi> 2, 3, 4, 5.</note> 
               <hi>in theſe laſt perillous times</hi> (according to the Apoſtles prediction) to <hi>be ſelf-lovers, proud, boaſters, diſobedient to Parents, without natural affection, falſe accuſers, fierce, deſpiſers of thoſe that are good, traitours, heady, high-minded, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:93632:19"/>indeed a form of godlineſs, but denying the power thereof;</hi> had I but time to demonſtrate theſe things, as it were eaſie both by <hi>Scripture,</hi> plain <hi>Reaſon,</hi> Eccleſiaſtical <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> and our own certain <hi>Experience</hi> of the like Events from the ſame Cauſes, in the late times of Liberty and Confuſion, <hi>I</hi> ſhould clearly make it appear unto you, That this irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar <hi>itching humour of Curioſity,</hi> and <hi>affecting of novelties</hi> is, though not ſo ſcandalous in the ſight of men, yet as hainous in the ſight of God, and miſchievous to Peoples Souls as any Crime that they can lightly be guilty of. For <hi>it's by this</hi> (<hi>as the</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Math. 15.6.</note> 
               <hi>grand Tradition of the late Scribes and Elders</hi> amongſt us) that the <hi>Phariſaical Men of this Generation</hi> have made the Commandments and Precepts of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning good Order, Diſcipline, and Decency in the Church, concerning Subjection and Obedience to Civil Magiſtrates, concerning Affection and due Reverence towards Chriſts Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, concerning brotherly Love and Union amongſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Neighbours, <hi>of none effect.</hi> I ſpeak nothing but what is notoriouſly known to be <hi>Truth,</hi> by all unintereſſed, judicious, ſober and ſolid Chriſtians. And therefore no wonder, that Gods anger is waxed thus hot, and his jealouſie burn like fire againſt ſuch a refractory, obſtinately erroneous, and indeed antichriſtian a generation as this: <hi>Which</hi> may very well (in the<note n="g" place="margin">Math. 11.16, 17.</note> words of our Saviour) <hi>be likened unto Children ſitting in the Market-place, and calling unto their fellows, and ſaying, We have piped unto you, and ye have not danced; We have mourned unto you, and ye have not lamented.</hi> For, even ſo in this age, we find one party ſtill oppoſing, countermining, and walking con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to another: So that let Chriſt ſend what <hi>Labourers</hi> ſoever He pleaſe <hi>into his harveſt,</hi> though never ſo innocent, honeſt, able, and faithfull; though never ſo carefull to follow His, and His bleſſed Apoſtles example, and that in reſpect both of Life and Doctrine; though never ſo conſcientious in the performance of all Miniſterial Offices and Duties, according to His expreſs direction, the infallible and harmonious tenour and Canon of Scripture, to the great comfort and ſatisfaction of all humble-minded and honeſt-hearted perſons amongſt us; who therefore<note n="h" place="margin">1 Theſſ. 5.13.</note> 
               <hi>eſteem them very highly in love, for their works ſake, and count</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">1 Tim. 5.17.</note> 
               <hi>them worthy of double honour:</hi> Yet the devout
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:93632:20"/>
               <hi>Will-worſhippers,</hi> and religious<note n="k" place="margin">2 Pet. 2.10. with Jude <hi>v.</hi> 8.</note> 
               <hi>deſpiſers of Government,</hi> in theſe dayes, who to compaſs their ends, and carry on their deſigns, are <hi>not afraid to ſpeak evil of Dignities,</hi> preferring Novelty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Antiquity, a Formal Shew above Reality, Self-intereſt and worldly Reputation, before Gods Acceptance and Approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; theſe will evermore have one fault or other to finde with them, and rather than fail, invent and forge reproaches and ſcandals, that ſo they may have ſome plauſible pretence <hi>to</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Pſal. 2.3.</note> 
               <hi>break their bands aſunder, and caſt away their Cords from them.</hi> Now, what is this, but in effect to tell our Saviour, that they are grown weary of <hi>His Government</hi> and <hi>Oeconomy,</hi> and now <hi>will have</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Luk 19.14.</note> 
               <hi>Him no longer to reign over them,</hi> unleſs He'l ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of a new way of Worſhip, according to ſome mode of their own that is now in faſhion: All other Forms, and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional Platforms, though never ſo authentick, and apparently <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> are counted by them to be but Idolatrous and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious. And then,</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>For that flat Obſtinacy, and open Rebellion againſt lawfull Magiſtrates, the Higher Powers that God hath ſet over us:</hi> Though I know none at preſent actually guilty of it, yet that muſt be attributed not ſo much to the happy change of many mens mindes, or any peaceable and truly Chriſtian Principles in them, as rather to the good <hi>Providence of God,</hi> and the watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful wiſdom, courage and diligence of thoſe in Authority. Sure I am, there is no want of implacable Male-contents, and moſt turbulent-ſpirited Incendiaries amongſt us, to will and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour it; and with as much ſubtilty, malice, and ſecreſie as it is poſſible. <hi>They riſe up early and lye down late, and eat the bread of carefulneſs;</hi> they ſpare no pains, they ſtick at no difficulties nor dangers, but attempt and aſſay all ways and means; yea, they are ready <hi>to compaſs even Sea and Land,</hi> and all in hopes to compaſs their end. Nay, rather than fail to carry on their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, ſome there are that cunningly can <hi>transform themſelves into Angels of Light,</hi> to trapann the well-meaning ignorant vulgar unto their ſide: For which end, they very forwardly thruſt themſelves, or ſteal ſliely into our Pulpits, and there vehemently enough (it's true) inveigh againſt the groſs ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous ſins of Pride and Profaneneſs, Gluttony and Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Whoredom, Swearing, and Sabbath-breaking; ſtrongly
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:93632:20"/>inſinuating, that all but themſelves and thoſe of their Party, are certainly guilty of ſome of them, and ſo are in danger of Hell and Damnation: But the miſchief and wickedneſs of it is, that whileſt they thus openly pretend, that they come only <hi>to beat down ſin, and ſave peoples Souls,</hi> by perſwading them to <hi>a cloſe walking with God,</hi> and ſtrict <hi>Obedience to the Goſpel of Chriſt,</hi> they ſecretly withall intend to talk them out of all their Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance, love and duty towards their Superiours both in Church and State: they name and proclaim themſelves indeed, to be the <hi>Meſſengers of God, and Ambaſſadours of Jeſus Chriſt; but by their fruits we may eaſily judge whoſe Emiſſaries they are,</hi> in that the main drift and tendency of their preaching is to diſpoſe and work poor people into a murmuring againſt, a ſlighting of, and diſobedience to all humane and Eccleſiaſtical Conſtitutions, let them be never ſo reaſonable, never ſo religious, and conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taneous to Gods holy Word. And all (forſooth) under the ſpecious fair pretenſe, that primarily all people are the ſubjects and ſervants of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt, and ought to obey God rather than Man;</hi> as if the Commandments and Inſtitutions, the Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Diſcipline and holy Ordinances of Chriſt himſelf and his Apoſtles, being approved of, and inforced by the authority of thoſe that God hath ſet over us, muſt not, ought not then to be obeyed or obſerved by them, only becauſe they are re-im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed and required of them by the commendable and good Statutes of Chriſtian Magiſtrates. Before this was done, they could not but confeſs, that they were binding to the Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of all ſound Believers; but now they would rather have <hi>the Godly</hi> to think, that they are bound in Conſcience to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temn and oppoſe them. The full perſwaſion of which deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive and wicked Tenet, they never leave till they have frighted them into, with the frequent and terrible threats of <hi>Hell and Damnation.</hi> And if this be not a moſt provoking and crying ſin, I know nothing that is. If any here ſhall object, that I am very harſh and ſevere: give me leave to tell them, that I never was their Auditor my ſelf; but, as a fuller conviction, and a much ſtronger<note n="*" place="margin">Vox Populi, vox Dei.</note> teſtimony againſt them, I have always obſerved by the report and diſcourſe of many of their ſeduced followers, that this is the very ſenſe and meaning that they all pick out of their Sermons; and beſides, I have read ſome of their plauſible
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:93632:21"/>printed Papers my ſelf, but know not how to make any other conſtruction of them. If ſtill they plead the integrity and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity of their own hearts, as perfectly free from, and utterly ignorant and innocent of all ſuch evil intentions, as I alledge and charge upon them; let me tell them in the words of our Saviour, that <hi>they</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Luk. 9.55.</note> 
               <hi>know not what manner of ſpirit they are of;</hi> for moſt of them are as ſurely guilty, as he that once ſaid to the Prophet <hi>Eliſha,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">2 King. 8.13.</note> 
               <hi>But what is thy ſervant a Dog?</hi> And this I could very eaſily evince, and clearly demonſtrate, by referring them to their own, and others Experience about five or ſix and twenty years ago: when there were many as ſincere and zealous in their pretences for a thorow Reformation, for the CAUSE of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> as they termed it, for the advancement of Truth and the Goſpel, and for the ſalvation of Souls, as any poſſiby can be now; who yet afterwards ſaw, and confeſſed, and bewailed themſelves, for that they unadviſedly had been too acceſſory and inſtrumental to pull up the Flood-gates, and let in a deluge of Rebellion, Confuſion, and deſolation that enſued thereupon. Which I earneſtly wiſh, that all our hot, young Non-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts, and their affectionate factious followers would ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly lay well to heart, leſt a worſe Judgement than this of the Plague be inflicted upon us.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Laſtly, <hi>For that wilful Diſobedience, and general Apoſtaſie from the true God, and his holy Laws and Commandments;</hi> Never ſure were the <hi>Children of Iſrael</hi> more guilty of this, than the <hi>People of England</hi> are in theſe days. When, betwixt a great deal of blind Ignorance, practical Atheiſm, and open Profaneſs on the one hand, and a great deal of Hypocriſie, ſpiritual Pride, and Obſtinacy in errour on the other, the true Fear of God, Love to his Name, and Obedience to his righteous Laws and Statutes ſeem to be quite extinguiſhed amongſt us. O the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge of Sin and Wickedneſs that ſeems to have quite over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowed both City and Country! Where is the man that with <hi>Nathaniel,</hi> may well be called <hi>an Iſraelite indeed, as exerciſing himſelf</hi> (with St. <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>to have</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Act. 24.16.</note> 
               <hi>always a Conſcience void of offence both towards God, and towards men?</hi> It was the complaint of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God</hi> in ancient time, and his upbraiding expoſtulation with the Nation of the <hi>Jews;</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Jer. 2.10, 11, 12, 13.</note> 
               <hi>Paſs ye over the Iſles of Chittim, and ſee: ſend unto Kedar, and conſider diligently, and ſee if there
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:93632:21"/>be ſuch a thing</hi> as this in the whole world; <hi>Hath a Nation changed their gods, which are yet no Gods? But my people have changed their glory, for that which doth not profit. Be aſtoniſhed O ye Heavens at this, and be horribly afraid, be ye very deſolate, ſaith the Lord. For my people have committed two evils: they have forſaken Me, the Fountain of living waters, and hewn them out Ciſterns, broken Ciſterns that can hold no water.</hi> And it may be as juſtly ſaid and applyed to this Nation of ours. Wherefore, as he ſpeak<note n="r" place="margin">Jer. 9.12, 13, 14.</note> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>Who is the wiſe man that may underſtand this, and who is he to whom the mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken, that he may declare it, for what the Land periſheth, and is burnt up like a Wilderneſs, that none paſſeth thorow?</hi> And to this the <hi>Lord</hi> maketh anſwer, <hi>and ſaith, Becauſe men have forſaken my Law, which I ſet before them, and have not obeyed my voyce, neither walked therein; but have walked after the imagination of their own heart,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thus have I run through the forenamed ſix particular capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Crimes mentioned in the Scripture, whereby common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, or the mixt multitude, and Body politick of a Nation have provoked God to pour out his vials of wrath and fury in this manner upon them: And have likewiſe brought home my Diſcourſe, and made it appear apparently to you, that there are too too many amongſt us guilty of each of them. Not but that I believe we have <hi>our tens, our thirties,</hi> and <hi>our fifties of good and righteous perſons</hi> among us: For whoſe ſakes, I hope and truſt that <hi>Almighty God</hi> will in his due time look down from heaven in mercy upon us, and heal our Land. Now, for which of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid ſins <hi>this ſore judgement</hi> is laid upon us, I have given you mine Opinion already, and ſhall ſay no more, but (as I ſaid) leave you all to judge: but judge, I would have you, your ſelves chiefly rather than others. Charity towards them, and fervent Prayers for them would be very good and commendable in you, but faithfulneſs and impartiality towards your ſelves is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry neceſſary, and will be moſt profitable for you. And wherein any of you find your ſelves guilty, I beſeech you repent, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake your ſins, and turn unto God by prayers, and tears, and firm reſolutions; and then He will turn from the fierceneſs of his wrath. When every one ſweeps before his own door, the ſtreets you know, will quickly be clean; ſo let every one take but care to get <hi>the plague of his own heart</hi> cured, and then this ſad judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:93632:22"/>of the Plague and Peſtilence, ſhall be as quickly removed us. And ſo I have done with the third particular Subject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matter of our <hi>conſideration in the day of adverſity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <note place="margin">4. The end of it.</note>4. The fourth is, <hi>the end of it, or the mind and meaning of God therein.</hi> And that may be either 1. For the tryal, the fatherly chaſtiſement and correction of ſome, <hi>viz.</hi> the righteous, his own true Children and Servants. For<note n="s" place="margin">Prov. 3.12. &amp; Heb. 12.6, 7, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>whom the Lord loveth, he cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recteth; even as a Father the Son in whom he delighteth.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s good counſel is,<note n="t" place="margin">1 Pet. 4.12, 13.</note> 
               <hi>Beloved, think it not ſtrange con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the fiery tryal, which is to try you, as though ſome ſtrange thing happened unto you: But rejoyce, inaſmuch as ye are partakers of Chriſts ſufferings.</hi> Or elſe 2. For the juſt puniſhment and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of others, <hi>viz</hi> the wicked and ungodly; according to that of <hi>Job,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Job 31.3. &amp; Prov. 1.24, &amp;c. &amp; Iſa 1.19, 20.</note> 
               <hi>Is not deſtruction to the wicked, and a ſtrange puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the workers of iniquity?</hi> Or 3. laſtly, generally and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly for the amendment and Inſtruction of all. The Apoſtle obſerves, that when the Father of Spirits afflicts and corrects the children of men, <hi>It is</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Heb. 12.10.</note> 
               <hi>for their profit, that ſo they may be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of his holineſs:</hi> And the Prophet tells us, <hi>That</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Iſa. 26.9.</note> 
               <hi>when Gods judgements are in the earth, the end thereof is, that the inhabitants of the world may learn righteouſneſs.</hi> And hence it is that God in Scripture is ſometimes compared to a<note n="*" place="margin">Quod iguis auro, hoc ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mabus eſt affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctio.</note> 
               <hi>Refiner, Mal.</hi> 3.3. and ſometimes to a <hi>Threſher,</hi> Hab. 3.12. <hi>Whoſe fan is in his hand, that he may thorowly purge his floor, but gather his wheat into his garner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">
               <note place="margin">5. The way to have it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved.</note>5. The laſt is, the good way and means that we are to uſe, that ſo it may be removed from us, or at leaſt we may have it ſanctified to us. And for this I refer you for full ſatisfaction to the uſefull and ſeaſonable <hi>Exhortation,</hi> ſet forth by the Church, and approved by Authority. And ſo here at preſent it ſhal ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice briefly to tell you, that the ways and means are of two ſorts in general. 1. Moral and natural; ſuch as our own diſcretion and reaſon prompt us unto; or the experience, and more mature knowledge of others direct us unto. 2. Spiritual and Theologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal; and ſuch are patience and contentation, humble ſubmiſſion and ſelf-reſignation; earneſt prayer and ſupplications, with a-Amendment of life, and a real Reformation. I ſhall but barely name theſe things, becauſe I deſire to ſubjoyn ſomething by way of Motive to inforce the duty of <hi>Conſideration</hi> now in this <hi>diſmal day of Adverſity:</hi> As,</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:93632:22"/>
            <p n="1">1. There is nothing more proper and ſeaſonable for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent juncture of time;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mot.</hi> 1.</note> ſo much the Spirit of God here aſſures us. Now it is the Wiſemans well known compariſon,<note n="y" place="margin">Prov 25.11.</note> 
               <hi>Verbum opportunè dictum,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>A word fitly ſpoken is like Apples of Gold in pictures of Silver.</hi> And if <hi>words</hi> (which we ſay are but wind) only becauſe they are pertinent and ſeaſonable, be thus excellent, beautifull, and amiable in the eſteems of rational men: ſurely then, <hi>Opus opportune factum,</hi> a good work and duty ſeaſonably, ſeriouſly and well done and performed by us, is no leſs valuable in the account of <hi>Almighty God.</hi> It's very true, as the heathen Orator long ſince obſerved,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: Iſocr.</note> That what's out of ſeaſon, &amp; out of faſhion, ſeldom meets with peoples good liking and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation: but on the contrary,<note n="z" place="margin">Eccl. 3.11.</note> 
               <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us, <hi>that God hath made every thing beautifull in it's time.</hi> Such therefore is the Duty en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned here in this text; &amp; that very ſtrongly commends it to us.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There is nothing more excellent and commendable as to the work and duty it ſelf. <hi>Conſideration!</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mot.</hi> 2.</note> it is the ſearcher of the heart, the Manure of the Soul, the foſterer of zeal, the remedy againſt ſecurity, the improvement of Chriſtianity, the ladder of heaven, and the key of Paradiſe. <hi>Conſideration!</hi> it is as watering to Plants, as blowing to the Fire, as Oyl to ſtiffe joynts, as Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick to the ſick: It urgeth to repentance, quickeneth to Prayer, confirmeth Faith, kindleth Love, encourageth in well-doing, and refreſheth with heavenly conſolations.</p>
            <p n="3">3. There is nothing more well-pleaſing and acceptable to God. <hi>Enoch</hi> for this was rewarded with a<note n="†" place="margin">Gen. 5.24.</note> glorious <hi>tranſlation.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mot.</hi> 3.</note> And indeed for what end hath God given us <hi>the great things of his Law,</hi> committed to us <hi>his ſacred Oracles,</hi> cauſed the <hi>Scriptures</hi> to be written for our learning, ſent his <hi>Prophets</hi> to declare his good will and pleaſure to us; yea, ſent forth his <hi>Son</hi> to reveal his thoughts, which are thoughts of mercy, love &amp; peace to us<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward? Certainly, not that all theſe things ſhould be ſlighted by us, but pondered upon in our hearts, and well improved by a due and ſerious <hi>Conſideration.</hi> And the more we do ſo, the more without doubt we ſhall pleaſe him; this being the beſt way to honour him, and to expreſs our thankfulneſs to him for them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. There is nothing more neceſſary,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mot.</hi> 4.</note> nothing more advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious and profitable to our own ſouls, as was ſhew'd you before in the<note n="*" place="margin">Page 3, 4.</note> Introduction. Wherefore to conclude, would'ſt thou
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:93632:23"/>be bleſſed in all thy Enterprizes and Concernments with the <hi>bleſſings of God?</hi> would'ſt thou have thy <hi>underſtanding</hi> enlighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the knowledge of God? thine <hi>affections</hi> inflamed with the love of God, thine <hi>heart</hi> eſtabliſhed with the Promiſes of God, thy <hi>ſolitarineſs</hi> cheared up with the fellowſhip of God, thy <hi>afflictions</hi> ſweetned and mitigated with the comforts of God, and all thy <hi>thoughts, words,</hi> and <hi>actions</hi> regulated by the Commands of God? then let thy daily practice be to <hi>Pray and Conſider.</hi> For, <hi>in the day of adverſity,</hi> there is nothing <hi>then</hi> more proper and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, nothing <hi>then</hi> more excellent &amp; commendable, nothing <hi>then</hi> more well-pleaſing and acceptable, nothing <hi>then</hi> (no nor indeed at any time elſe) more advantagious, neceſſary and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable. Conſider therefore <hi>then</hi> eſpecially, and well and wiſely weigh with thy ſelf, 1. <hi>The evil, diſaſter, or viſitation it ſelf, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever it be, that is befalne thee.</hi> 2. <hi>The Diſpenſer and Author of it.</hi> 3. <hi>The ground, or the procuring and meritorious cauſe of it.</hi> 4. <hi>The End, or the mind and meaning of God therein: and</hi> 5. <hi>The good way and means that is to be uſed, that ſo it may be removed from thee, or elſe may be ſanctiſted to thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which five particulars, give me leave here to adde, in the cloſe of all, one Object more, which you may do well to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe your <hi>Conſideration</hi> upon; <hi>Conſider the Poor,</hi> the afflicted mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> Whoſe wants, and whoſe number are very much increaſed ſince this ſad time of <hi>Viſitation;</hi> and whoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition you may eaſily imagine muſt needs be ſo exceeding help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and deplorable, (ſince all trading and employments are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt quite dead and gone) that there never was more reaſon for <hi>the Rich to conſider the Poor:</hi> And for your incouragement know,<note n="b" place="margin">Prov. 19.17.</note> 
               <hi>That he that hath pity upon the Poor, lendeth unto the Lord, and that which he hath given will he pay him again.</hi> Neither ſhall it go without a Bleſſing in this world, as an Overplus; for,<note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 41.1, 2.</note> 
               <hi>Bleſſed is the man that conſidereth the poor; the Lord will deliver him in the time of trouble: Yea, the Lord will preſerve him, and keep him alive, and he ſhall be bleſſed upon the Earth.</hi> I, and for a further encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement ſtill, I paſs my word and promiſe to you beforehand, That what you ſhal give ſhal not go out of the Pariſh, but ſhal be expended and beſtowed upon our own Poor; for ſo, I am ſure, the Receiver General appointed by his Majeſty, the can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did and untainted Right Reverend Biſhop of this Dioceſs, will be well-pleaſed that<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Octob.</hi> 4. 1665.</note> henceforth it ſhould be diſpoſed of.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
